<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A speech without-doors, or, Some modest inquiries humbly proposed to the right honourable the Convention of Estates, assembled at Westminster, Jan. 22, 1688/9 concerning, I. Bigotism, or religious madness, II. Tests, and the present test in particular, III. Penal laws in matters of religion, IV. The necessity of changing and recanting our opinions in religion, V. Restraint of the press / by Edm. Hickeringill ...</title>
            <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20396</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12444503</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12444503</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62182</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43636)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62182)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 942:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A speech without-doors, or, Some modest inquiries humbly proposed to the right honourable the Convention of Estates, assembled at Westminster, Jan. 22, 1688/9 concerning, I. Bigotism, or religious madness, II. Tests, and the present test in particular, III. Penal laws in matters of religion, IV. The necessity of changing and recanting our opinions in religion, V. Restraint of the press / by Edm. Hickeringill ...</title>
                  <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Larkin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62182:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A SPEECH Without-DOORS:</hi> OR SOME Modeſt Inquiries Humbly Propoſed to The RIGHT HONOURABLE THE <hi>Convention of Eſtates,</hi> Aſſembled at WESTMINSTER, <hi>Jan.</hi> 22. 1688/9.</p>
            <p>CONCERNING,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <label>I.</label> 
                     <hi>Bigotiſm, or Religious Madneſs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>II.</label> 
                     <hi>Teſts, and the Preſent Teſt in Particular.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>III.</label> 
                     <hi>Penal Laws in Matters of Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>IV.</label> 
                     <hi>The Neceſſity of Changing and Recanting our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>V.</label> 
                     <hi>Reſtraint of the Preſs.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDM. HICKERINGILL, <hi>Rector of the Rectory of</hi> All Saints <hi>in</hi> Colcheſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin,</hi> at the <hi>Two Swans</hi> without <hi>Biſhopſgate.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62182:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62182:2"/>
            <head>To the Illuſtrious, Right Honourable, and Honourable, The <hi>Convention of Eſtates,</hi> Aſſembled at <hi>WESTMINSTER, <hi>Jan.</hi>
               </hi> 22. 1688.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Illuſtrious, Right Honourable, and Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOr as much as <hi>you</hi> are Esteemed (by <hi>the whole Body</hi> of the People) the wiſest and honesteſt, and therefore <hi>the moſt able</hi> and proper) <hi>Healers of our preſent Breaches</hi> and Diſtractions, ſo you cannot bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>approve</hi> your ſelves <hi>ſuch, than</hi> by the <hi>beſt Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monal</hi> thereof (that Poſſibly can be, viz.) <hi>Moderation:</hi> For no Extreams <hi>laſt long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Paſſion, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Self-Intereſt</hi> (the boldest and worſt of <hi>Uſurpers)</hi> do come to be the Domineering and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing-Party,</hi> then Right <hi>Reaſon</hi> (and conſequently true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Justice) <hi>are depos'd</hi> and <hi>dethron'd,</hi> and then comes Confuſion and every evill work.</p>
            <p>There never can be <hi>(nor ever were)</hi> more than <hi>two ſorts of</hi> Polititians in Chriſtendom: <hi>The one</hi> thinks <hi>Juſtice, Piety,</hi> and <hi>Honeſty</hi> the beſt Policy, as our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and <hi>all Chriſtians</hi> that follow <hi>their ſteps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other</hi> makes uſe of Juſtice and Religion too <hi>(ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times)</hi> but <hi>no further</hi> than they <hi>ſerve his Politick turn,</hi> his worldly greatneſs and glory; (which if Juſtice and Christian Religion will not bring to him, then he tries what Oppreſſion and Superstition will do: For <hi>this Brute</hi> (as if he had the <hi>Soul of a Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>not an Immortal</hi> Soul) never looks up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nor <hi>takes his meaſures</hi> from him that <hi>Made and Rules</hi> the World and the Kingdom of men, and <hi>giveth it to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will;</hi> but calculates all his Plots to the <hi>Glory of this World,</hi> and terminates them <hi>in this life:</hi> And if his Plots and the Devil <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ail him,</hi> like <hi>Achitophet,</hi> he does (or is ready to) hang himſelf; or like that <hi>Brute,</hi> the King <hi>(Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>adnezzar)</hi> driven from his People, and turned to Graſs,
<pb facs="tcp:62182:3"/>like a Brute as he was, <hi>until he knew</hi> that the Moſt High R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the Kingdoms of men, and <hi>and giveth them to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour <hi>ſays</hi> his Kingdom <hi>is not of this World;</hi> when therefore we pray, <hi>Thy Kingdom come,</hi> we ought <hi>not to wiſh,</hi> much leſs <hi>endeavour,</hi> that <hi>Antichriſt's Kingdom ſhould come.</hi> But in carrying on True and Pure Religion and the Goſpel, we ought to <hi>content our ſelves with ſuch</hi> Engines wherewith <hi>Chriſt and the Apoſtles</hi> propagated the ſame, <hi>all the World over,</hi> three hundred years before <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was born.</p>
            <p>Nor ought we to follow the Antichristian ſteps of the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Turk.</hi> For <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or the <hi>man of Sin,</hi> are ſurely nouns <hi>of multitude,</hi> accumulative words, and ſignifie thoſe that carry on a <hi>Superſtition</hi> contrary to <hi>Chriſt's Religion;</hi> they are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, or <hi>againſt Chriſt;</hi> and they that ſit <hi>in the Temple of God,</hi> (God's Throne) <hi>commanding Souls and Conſciences,</hi> as if they were Gods; they are <hi>limbs of that man of ſin;</hi> which ſhall fall, by the Finger of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which Finger of God</hi> was never more apparently and <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly ſeen,</hi> than in this late Revolution, which is like a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the Dead; <hi>Dead,</hi> I ſay, (for both <hi>we, and our</hi> irreconcileable <hi>Adverſaries</hi> had <hi>paſt the Sentence of Death</hi> upon us, unreprievable without a Miracle;) And whoever treads in the Antichristian ſteps and <hi>Policies of the Man of Sin,</hi> by Propagating the Goſpel with <hi>force of Arms,</hi> can they expect other than to <hi>ſtand or fall</hi> with ſuch ill Company? But as our <hi>Riders</hi> are chang'd, we hope alſo to have our heavy Burdens, and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Loads taken off. For, by force chiefly <hi>Antichriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> made Converts, with his <hi>Alcoran</hi> (or Bible) <hi>in one hand,</hi> and his Sword <hi>in the other,</hi> (with this motto) If <hi>one will not do,</hi> the <hi>other ſhall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Turk</hi> makes Converts, with <hi>Conſtables,</hi> Hangmen, <hi>Jaylors,</hi> Penal Laws, <hi>Teſts,</hi> and Troops of <hi>Dragoons.</hi> Will <hi>the bolder Engliſh</hi> never be wiſer than to follow <hi>French-Faſhions?</hi> Shall nothing be the <hi>mode here,</hi> (no, <hi>not in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion neither,)</hi> but what is <hi>A-la-mode de Francois?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62182:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Never had any</hi> Engliſhmen a greater <hi>Truſt put upon</hi> them, nor a greater <hi>Power put into their</hi> hands, than <hi>is put into yours</hi> this day, in this extraordinary, rare, <hi>neceſſary</hi> (and therefore) <hi>Juſt Convention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have <hi>virtually in you,</hi> the power of <hi>all the Laws,</hi> and all the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> that <hi>ever were,</hi> or ever <hi>ſhall be</hi> again in <hi>England</hi> to the <hi>worlds End;</hi> becauſe, it is <hi>in your Breaſts,</hi> to ſave, <hi>deſtroy,</hi> continue or <hi>abrogate them,</hi> or <hi>any of them,</hi> arbitrarily <hi>at your good pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It becomes not me</hi> to determine <hi>poſitively,</hi> whether the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy be diſſolv'd</hi> by the Kings d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>parture, <hi>throwing up the Reynes of Government,</hi> and will <hi>Guide no longer, quitting the Helm</hi> of Empire, and leaving the ſhip <hi>(once more)</hi> to the <hi>mercy of the Waves,</hi> to ſink or <hi>Swim;</hi> refuſing to call <hi>Parliaments</hi> (the <hi>only Scourge</hi> of Evil Courcellors) and <hi>in whom</hi> jonytly, <hi>with himſelf,</hi> was lodg'd the <hi>Ligiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power:</hi> Or, Whether <hi>the General Revolt</hi> had taken from him the <hi>Power of Guidance,</hi> forfeited by <hi>Male-Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Executive Power</hi> of the Laws: Or, whether alſo <hi>the Invading</hi> of the <hi>Legiſlative Power</hi> by erecting a <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power,</hi> which ſeems, <hi>in effect,</hi> but a <hi>New Name</hi> for a <hi>New Legiſlative Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Executive Power <hi>of our Laws was (by our late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution) lodg'd in the King alone, (as the</hi> Sole Power <hi>of the</hi> Militia, <hi>making Alliances, Judges, Sheriffs,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>a</hi> Burden <hi>(thought to be)</hi> too heavy for any ſingle Shoulder, <hi>and has oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd</hi> two or three general Revolts, <hi>and Expulſions of the Monarchs</hi> in the three laſt Raigns; <hi>for the Males Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof (as was at leaſt pretended) together with</hi> other ſad Conſequences, <hi>too</hi> diſmal <hi>to be</hi> remembred here, <hi>and</hi> too lately done <hi>to be</hi> forgot; <hi>nor</hi> need we <hi>mention the</hi> many and general Revolts <hi>in our Fore-Fathers times,</hi> during all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Raigns <hi>ſince</hi> William <hi>the Firſt; all of them ariſing</hi> from the ſame occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet,</hi> will it not well become your Wiſdoms, quaerere vias an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquas, <hi>to</hi> keep to the old frame <hi>of Government,</hi> Monarchical;
<pb facs="tcp:62182:4"/>
               <hi>(with what</hi> limits of the Executive Power <hi>you ſhall pleaſe;) and (as</hi> near as may be <hi>with any convenience) to</hi> the old line too, <hi>and next Heir?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not only,</hi> becauſe a more awful Deference <hi>and Veneration is paid to (what is anciently)</hi> the Royal Family; <hi>than to any</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtart Family; <hi>but becauſe the</hi> Finger of God ſeems to point out, <hi>and direct to that Incomparable and Bleſſed</hi> Branch <hi>(thereof)</hi> which God has made ſo ſtrong for his own Self; <hi>and the chief Inſtrument in</hi> the Hand of the Almighty, <hi>for our</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <hi>from</hi> Popery and Slavery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nothing</hi> (here hinted at) <hi>is to</hi> inform your Wiſer <hi>Judgments, that knows much more of this already,</hi> (far be ſuch Vanity from me!) <hi>But to</hi> ſtir up <hi>your Affections, and to be</hi> One of your <hi>Humble</hi> Remembrancers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For every man is now</hi> (or never) <hi>concern'd to</hi> put to <hi>his helping Hand</hi> at this Dead Life, <hi>and you concern'd to</hi> accept kindly <hi>the Service</hi> (even of the Weakeſt) <hi>at leaſt, ſurely the</hi> least you can do, <hi>is to thank them for</hi> their Love and good Will, <hi>though</hi> no otherwiſe <hi>ſerviceable unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beſides, A</hi> Slip now <hi>may be</hi> fatal; <hi>or (at beſt)</hi> not ſo cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>hereafter</hi> as now; <hi>and</hi> as is more particularly <hi>inſiſted on in the</hi> Concluſion <hi>of this Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I well know, that <hi>in this Criſis,</hi> every <hi>Politick Noddle</hi> is pregnant with <hi>Projects,</hi> &amp; never <hi>at reſt,</hi> till it be <hi>delivered of his Minerva,</hi> which perhaps proves <hi>a Maggot.</hi> Yet, if what is now ſaid, be <hi>evidenc'd beyond all Contradiction</hi> and Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion other than (the old <hi>Antichriſtian Engine)</hi> a Jayl be pleaſed to protect the Author from ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Scholar-like, &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Confutation, until theſe Inquiries be oppugned with the <hi>only proper weapons,</hi> in Spiritual matters, <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> and <hi>Right Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lords (the preſent Biſhops, for the generality of them) have approved themſelves (in this juncture) not only moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> but excellent <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> notwithſtanding the Now-Church-of-<hi>England's-Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Paſſive Obedience; (without exception)</hi> and the <hi>only Weapon-ſalve</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:62182:4"/>Prayers and <hi>Tears</hi> (a good Doctrine <hi>for him</hi> indeed that is <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt</hi> right or wro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g); and finding the neceſſity of Recant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame; <hi>ſome of them</hi> (at least) have <hi>in good time</hi> betaken themſelves to a keener weapon; and the reſt (and thoſe) <hi>the beſt of them,</hi> are willing to <hi>come to a temper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby they do by Implication confeſs a too feavouriſh <hi>and</hi> hot diſtemper (that <hi>has</hi> been) 'tis <hi>now time,</hi> to come to the cooler and <hi>milder Galaxye</hi> (or <hi>milkye way)</hi> the <hi>only Way</hi> to Heaven.</p>
            <p>And if any thing, <hi>in theſe modeſt Inquiries,</hi> may tend <hi>to our Cure,</hi> no <hi>moderate Church of</hi> England-<hi>man</hi> can poſſibly be <hi>offended,</hi> except they are <hi>paſt cure</hi> and paſt <hi>'mending;</hi> to ſuch <hi>we have nothing to ſay,</hi> but to write, <hi>Lord have mercy</hi> —upon their Doors.</p>
            <p>Not only the <hi>welbeing,</hi> but the being of theſe Nations, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend much upon the ſucceſs of this moſt <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and moſt <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Convention,</hi> which has ſo <hi>many</hi> (and thoſe ſo great) <hi>Friends</hi> and Enemies.</p>
            <p>And is it not now high time to <hi>enlarge our Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>widen</hi> the Church of <hi>England's Pale,</hi> and not exclude (out of the Church and the Priviledges of it) <hi>the better half</hi> of the Nation? Is not this <hi>Piety?</hi> Nay, Is not this <hi>true</hi> wiſdom and honeſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy?</hi> Now, <hi>(now I ſay)</hi> when the <hi>Irreconcileable Enemies</hi> of our Holy Religion are (by <hi>cruel and bloody</hi> Confederacy) bandied and <hi>knotted together,</hi> to deſtroy us and our Religion Root and Branch?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brittain</hi> was never conquer'd <hi>but by her ſelf.</hi> How? By her divided Parties, ſaith <hi>Tacitus,</hi> (the beſt Roman Hiſtorian of the Romiſh Conqueſt over <hi>Britain)</hi> ſmiling, <hi>Dum ſinguli pugnabant, omnes victi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not <hi>now</hi> therefore time to <hi>open the Church-doors as wide</hi> as Chriſt and his Holy Apostles opened them? Shall Filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luere, Pride or Malice <hi>ſhut them up,</hi> whilst monopolized to <hi>a few</hi> that ſhare <hi>all the Gains,</hi> though the Poor Diſsenter muſt partake the hazzard and the <hi>Pains,</hi> in our Common Defence? Even <hi>Private Soldiers</hi> fight <hi>coldly,</hi> without any <hi>Pay,</hi> or any <hi>hopes of Reward,</hi> in the Booty, after Victory.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62182:5"/>
            <p>Very excellent men <hi>(as it happens,</hi> which ſeldom happens in ſuch a Conſtitution of a Church) are now <hi>uppermoſt.</hi> But ſurely <hi>we are not obliged to believe</hi> all that they ſay who happen to be uppermost, <hi>only becauſe they are uppermoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, though <hi>at preſent</hi> we have (for the generality of our <hi>Fathers</hi> in the Church) at <hi>this</hi> time very good men, yet <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times</hi> the very <hi>Froth and Skum</hi> may be uppermoſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore if <hi>ſome errors</hi> in our Church, both peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in <hi>Doctrine</hi> as well as <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> be humbly inquired into, (if they appear upon moderate deliberation to be <hi>Errors</hi>) muſt we <hi>continue</hi> in them, or <hi>curſe our ſelves</hi> to an eternal conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance <hi>therein,</hi> or (as in the Office of <hi>Commination</hi> in the Common-Prayer-Book) ſay, <hi>Amen,</hi> still, (ſo be it <hi>Amen,)</hi> Is it not better to ſay, <hi>Amend, Amend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this Cauſe the <hi>Author</hi> humbly hopes that you will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the <hi>nice formality</hi> of Printing this <hi>without an Imprimatur,</hi> which cannot in any likelyhood be obtained from the <hi>preſent</hi> Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, if any thing here thwart their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and ſpoil <hi>their Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To your <hi>Unbyaſſed</hi> and Impartial Reaſons therefore, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> humbly <hi>appeals;</hi> And what <hi>Book</hi> or <hi>Author</hi> would deſire to <hi>live,</hi> if cast and <hi>condemn'd</hi> by <hi>ſuch Judges?</hi> And <hi>who dare</hi> condemn, whom your <hi>better Judgments</hi> think meet to <hi>ſave?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>following Eſſays</hi> are moſt <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi> as to the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter</hi> inquired into: But, if for want of <hi>dexterity,</hi> they be <hi>ill handled,</hi> yet be pleaſed <hi>not to diſcourage</hi> this well-meant and <hi>humble attempt</hi> (here laid at <hi>your Feet</hi>) ſince <hi>(at worſt)</hi> it may ſerve for a <hi>Prompter</hi> to put <hi>better Heads</hi> in mind, and to ſet <hi>better Tongues</hi> at work to <hi>diſcourſe</hi> the <hi>point</hi> more accurately <hi>within</hi> your Walls, which is now only <hi>A Speech without-Doors, by</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ready Servant, <hi>E. Hickeringil.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62182:5"/>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>Of Bigotiſm, or Religious Madneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A <hi>Bigot?</hi> What's that? 'Tis a Spiritual <hi>Narciſſus;</hi> a Self-conceited Religious Coxcomb, that <hi>falling in love</hi> with the <hi>ſhadows</hi> and Whimſes, Opinions and <hi>Imaginations</hi> of his <hi>own dear</hi> Crazy Skull, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion; <hi>Eſpouſes</hi> them to that height of Dotage, that he will Buſtle and <hi>fight like mad,</hi> and in the Quarrel wilingly <hi>dye</hi> a ſilly <hi>Martyr</hi> too; at leaſt, will freely venture Life and Limb, Goods and Lands (though he had <hi>Kingdoms to ſtake</hi>) yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowing <hi>why</hi> nor <hi>wherefore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this Spiritual <hi>Bankrupt takes up all</hi> his ſtock of Religion <hi>upon Truſt,</hi> and at all adventures, <hi>without</hi> ground or <hi>reaſon,</hi> other then <hi>Education,</hi> or ſome <hi>wilder</hi> chance, and therefore believes a <hi>Lye</hi> as eagerly and firmly as <hi>the greateſt Truth,</hi> and had been a <hi>Mahometan,</hi> if born in <hi>Turky;</hi> a <hi>Papiſt, Moor</hi> or <hi>Jew,</hi> if born in <hi>Portugal,</hi> and an <hi>Infidel</hi> in <hi>China.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this <hi>Spiritual Lunatick</hi> wants Power and <hi>Authority,</hi> he plays his Religious Pranks and Freaques only in <hi>apiſh</hi> Tricks and <hi>devout Mimickry,</hi> skiping perhaps from the Shop board to the Pulpit, where the <hi>mad Ape</hi> makes ſuch <hi>Faces and Grimaces,</hi> quoting of Holy Scripture, and Commenting thereupon, as Frenzically, impertinently and Fanatically, as <hi>Olivers Porter</hi> in <hi>Bedlam;</hi> and if a ſtranger (that is not us'd to it) ſhould ſpy him there, he might Swear, and ſafely too (in the words of <hi>Hoſea</hi>) <hi>The Prophet is a fool, and the Spiritual man is mad,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62182:6"/>or (more properly and according to the original) <hi>The man of the Spirit is mad;</hi> and being <hi>craz'd with a notion</hi> (like <hi>Archimedes</hi>) runs skiping about, Crying, <hi>Eureka, Eureka,</hi> I have it, <hi>I have found it;</hi> when <hi>nothing is found</hi> but the ſoft place in his head.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Magiſtracy and Authority</hi> ſhall happen at any time to <hi>be poſſeſt</hi> with this <hi>mad ſpirit</hi> of Superſtitious <hi>Lunacy:</hi> Then for <hi>Propagation</hi> nothing leſs will ſerve then to <hi>encreaſe and multiply</hi> this ſpurious Iſſue (and <hi>Baſtard Minerva</hi> of their Prieſt-ridden <hi>Brayns</hi>) amongſt all their Inferiours and <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants; Impoſing</hi> Creed and <hi>Faith,</hi> as Magiſterially as great <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf, making believers and <hi>Faith by Statute-Law,</hi> Cannon-Law; which they muſt and ſhall believe in ſpight of their hearts, or elſe by <hi>Penal Laws</hi> take what follows, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Anathema, Fire and Faggot, as leaſt, <hi>Hell and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> Fines and Impriſonments; but, <hi>Put up thy dagger,</hi> Bigot!</p>
               <p>Does not <hi>Antichriſt</hi> thus ſet up the <hi>Abomination of Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the holy place (the Chymera's of his Noddle <hi>in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God) where he ſits,</hi> commanding Faith and Conſciences,) as Peremtorily and Infallibly <hi>as if he were God;</hi> breathing Vengeance, and ſpitting Fire at all that oppoſe him, and like a diſtracted <hi>Indian</hi> Bigot, <hi>runing a Mack</hi> at all Mankind, <hi>till he kill</hi> (or be kill'd by) all that <hi>ſtand in his way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Bigotted Spaniard</hi> converted the <hi>Indies</hi> with a <hi>long Tuck;</hi> and thus the hair-brain'd <hi>French</hi> in Bloody Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Popedom</hi> (of Two Millions of Hereticks) Confuted and Extirpated <hi>Two hundred Thouſand</hi> of them, and made <hi>Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Hundred Thouſand</hi> new Converts, with <hi>Troops of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſſeſt</hi> with this Evil <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Bigotiſme</hi> and devout Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy, King <hi>Manaſſah</hi> Sacrific'd his Son to <hi>Moloch</hi> in the Flames; And King <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> gave up his Son to be Murthered in the Bloody <hi>Inqueſition,</hi> upon ſuſpition of <hi>Lutheraniſm:</hi> And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62182:6"/>
                  <hi>what Spirit poſſeſt</hi> our Neighbour Nation, when no man was Suffer'd <hi>to buy or ſell,</hi> or give meat or drink or other Comfort to any whom <hi>holy Church</hi> had Excommunicated? Nay, <hi>at home</hi> here—How now? No more; <hi>Hold there:</hi> Come not near.</p>
               <p>It is as ſafe to <hi>Kennel</hi> with a mad <hi>Bull-dog,</hi> or with the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in the <hi>Tower,</hi> or cohabit with a Mad-man in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> as with a <hi>Zealous</hi> and Furious <hi>Bigot;</hi> there is <hi>no living with him</hi> or near him, except he be muzled, fetter'd or chain'd; for <hi>if he break looſe,</hi> all the ſober part of mankind are concern'd <hi>to joyn hands</hi> in their own defence; and in Self-Preſervation <hi>to tye him up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if I have here made a <hi>Whip of ſmall Cords</hi> to laſh this <hi>Tom of Bedlam</hi> out of the <hi>Church</hi> where he has made <hi>ſuch havock</hi> and diſturbance with his <hi>magot;</hi> it is but in order <hi>to his cure,</hi> by gentle <hi>ſtripes</hi> to bring him (if poſſible) <hi>to his wits</hi> again, and to reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> (I ſay) which is <hi>the Souls best Centinel,</hi> which ſhould carefully <hi>examine</hi> every thing <hi>before it enter,</hi> ſtrictly <hi>challenging</hi> (not <hi>who</hi> but) what <hi>comes there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing is more frequently inculcated in Scripture, than <hi>Examine your ſelves, prove your own ſelves, try the Spirits whether they are of God:</hi> but for want of this, Popery, Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, and Bigotiſm has been the Inveterate and Old Diſeaſe of Chriſtendom; for <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prieſtcraft</hi> always preacht up <hi>Ignorance,</hi> as the only <hi>Mother</hi> (and ſo it is) of <hi>Bigotiſm</hi> and ſilly <hi>Devotion: Samſon</hi> muſt firſt have <hi>his Eyes put out,</hi> before he can be managed <hi>to make ſport.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am ſenſible, that I treat of a Subject that is <hi>ſeldom or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> handled <hi>in this method,</hi> and of a Diſtemper, that will make the mad-men <hi>rage the more;</hi> there is witchcraſt in this <hi>frenzy,</hi> they are ſo bewitcht as to be <hi>in love</hi> with their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe and will, like other <hi>Lunaticks (to chooſe)</hi> fall upon the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> above all others, if he attempt <hi>to cure them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62182:7"/>
               <p>But is it not a Lunacy <hi>beyond</hi> the wild <hi>fury of Bedlam,</hi> that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould <hi>now</hi> think of <hi>new farbuſhing</hi> and whetting the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Diſſenters</hi> to their <hi>Placet's, arbitrary</hi> and wilfull <hi>Impoſitions</hi> in doubtful and trivial matters, <hi>Lana caprina,</hi> and <hi>Bar them out</hi> of the Church and State (their Birth-rights <hi>as Men and Christians</hi>) with <hi>Teſts</hi> (deſign'd at <hi>first only</hi> againſt the irreconcileable <hi>Enemies of our Religion</hi>) and (when the <hi>Oath of Supremacy alone</hi> will do <hi>the feat</hi>) ſtraitning the Church of <hi>England to a few,</hi> (is it that <hi>they alone</hi> may monopolize <hi>all the Preferments</hi> in Church and State) when <hi>all the Wiſdom,</hi> Piety and Policy in the World cries aloud <hi>to widen the Churches Pale</hi> and enlarge her Intereſt, <hi>now, now eſpecially,</hi> when the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> has drawn a <hi>Sword never to be ſheath'd</hi> but in our <hi>Throats?</hi> Shall <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot, Gen.</hi> 13.7. be at ſtrife <hi>between themſelves</hi> about trifles, when the <hi>Canaanite</hi> and <hi>Perizzite</hi> is ready <hi>to Land?</hi> Is it <hi>not yet</hi> time to <hi>looſe the hands of wickedneſs, to undo the heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, to let the Oppreſſed go free, and to break every</hi> (Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Bigotted) <hi>Yoak?</hi> Iſai. 58.6. Read ſeriouſly <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. the whole Chapter is <hi>an approved Cure,</hi> for Dogmatical and Pragmatical <hi>Bigotiſm.</hi> We read in <hi>Scripture,</hi> that all Chriſtians ſhould endeavour to <hi>keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace;</hi> but where do we read that any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did, or ought <hi>to Compel <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, as the Bond of Peace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>Hold</hi>—may ſome ſay, and have a care; whilſt you ſpeak againſt <hi>Bigotted Impoſitions,</hi> do you not tranſgreſs the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Church of</hi> England; that ſays, <hi>The Church has Power to Impoſe Rites and Ceremonies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, That it is <hi>time enough</hi> to anſwer that, when you have read what is ſaid concerning the ſame <hi>here,</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and Third <hi>Section;</hi> and alſo when any good Body <hi>(that can tell)</hi> will tell <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>who</hi> is this ſame <hi>Church of</hi> England? Who is the <hi>Head of it</hi> this day? And what <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62182:7"/>does a Head ſpeak, when it is <hi>ſeparated from,</hi> and not United with, nor of <hi>the ſame Complexion, Nutriment,</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> with the Body?</p>
               <p>Ay! But <hi>grant</hi> that <hi>what you ſay here be Truth,</hi> yet a grave Author ſays, <hi>That all Truths are not to be ſpoken at all times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And (Grave Author might <hi>to as wiſe purpoſe add</hi>) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>all Truths are not to be ſpoken at any time,</hi> when you touch the ſore place: No, no, they will always <hi>(then)</hi> kick; you'l <hi>pleaſe them at no time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Gypſees</hi> cant, and would <hi>gravely perſwade us</hi> to ſhut our Eyes and <hi>not diſcover</hi> their jugling Tricks, <hi>wink till ours,</hi> or our Friends <hi>Pockets</hi> be pickt; and then we ſhall have <hi>a Licenſe</hi> to diſcover the Naked Truth; Ay, Ay! <hi>(Dear Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity)</hi> but then it is <hi>too late.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>old Gentleman</hi> that was reſolved to <hi>dye a Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> ſilenc'd his Friends when they propos'd a Match for him in <hi>his Youth;</hi> Oh no, quoth he, It is not ſeaſonable, it is <hi>too ſoon</hi> to marry; but, when they reiterated the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal to him in his decrepit age, anſwers, Now you ſpeak <hi>too late;</hi> ſo that what men <hi>like not,</hi> is <hi>at no time ſeaſonable;</hi> they'l <hi>always</hi> quarrel <hi>with the time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are not things now, <hi>just now,</hi> upon the <hi>Hinge?</hi> Is not <hi>this time</hi> like the <hi>third and laſt time</hi> of Publiſhing the Banes of Matrimony? Either <hi>now Speak,</hi> or elſe <hi>forever hereafter</hi> hold your Peace.</p>
               <p>Reaſon <hi>(mans chiefest Light)</hi> ſhines <hi>bright enough</hi> in many <hi>mad men on one ſide of the skull,</hi> when it is benighted <hi>on the other ſide</hi> of the Pericranium, and <hi>craz'd</hi> with a notion <hi>on that ſide the head:</hi> Many mad-men in <hi>Bedlam</hi> will talk <hi>rationally enough,</hi> on <hi>any ſubject,</hi> except <hi>that</hi> which <hi>first beclouded</hi> their Reaſon; but then, when you <hi>touch upon that ſore place,</hi> they rave:</p>
               <p>Thus, it is reported of a <hi>mad-man</hi> that would <hi>talk moſt ſenſiby</hi> in <hi>all</hi> matters, except when <hi>he ſaw</hi> or diſcourſt of a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62182:8"/>
                  <hi>Ship</hi> (for he was <hi>craz'd</hi> by looſing his Eſtate <hi>by Ship-wrack</hi>) fancying that <hi>all</hi> mens <hi>Ships</hi> that came laden and <hi>well-fraught</hi> into the Port, were <hi>his own;</hi> and was <hi>as really overjoy'd,</hi> when the <hi>Rich Cargoes</hi> came home, <hi>as if they</hi> had truly been <hi>his own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His dear Friends, (pitying his diſtraction) got him cured, <hi>whether he would or no:</hi> Whereupon coming to his Right Mind, he thus thanked his Friends for their love to him— <hi>Pol me Periistis, amici!</hi> you have undone me, <hi>Dear Friends!</hi> and beggar'd me; yet he <hi>lost nothing</hi> but his <hi>Wild Fancy;</hi> ſurely, he was <hi>madder</hi> for ſaying ſo, <hi>than he was before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, to apply it; If any <hi>Church-of-England man,</hi> puffed up with <hi>Bigotiſm</hi> and <hi>mad-conceit</hi> of the Purity of what ſome call <hi>Church-of-England,</hi> both in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> and (like the whimſical Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi>) fancying that ſhe is <hi>Rich, and encreaſed in Goods, and hath need of nothing;</hi> and I (amongſt others) like <hi>a true Friend,</hi> endeavour <hi>to cure</hi> him of <hi>this Wild Fancy,</hi> and diſpel the <hi>Cloud</hi> that <hi>ſhadowed</hi> Right Reaſon, giving him to underſtand, beyond all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and as clear as day, <hi>how</hi> and <hi>wherein,</hi> both in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> ſhe is wretched, and miſerable, poor, and <hi>blind,</hi> and naked.</p>
               <p>That ſo, <hi>ſhe may betake her ſelf</hi> to wiſe Councels, and get Gold <hi>tryed in the Fire</hi> (that her Hay and Stubble being burnt up, (for <hi>ſhe muſt paſs through Purgatory here,</hi> and through the Furnace,) that ſhe may be <hi>rich;</hi> and White Rayment to cover the <hi>ſhame of her nakedneſs,</hi> that it may <hi>no longer appear;</hi> and anoynt the Eyes of our dim Mother, with Eye-ſalve <hi>that ſhe may ſee</hi> the better: Will any <hi>(in their wits)</hi> blame a <hi>true Son of the Church</hi> for his love and kindneſs <hi>to his pur-blind Mother;</hi> which is his Duty? And ſay, in her name—<hi>Pol me Peristi mi Fili:</hi> Verily, verily, you have undone me, dear Son! Surely, ſuch a <hi>mad</hi> and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>exclamation</hi> would ſpeak her to be <hi>incurable,</hi> and would aggravate the <hi>Diſtraction.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62182:8"/>
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>Of</hi> TESTS, <hi>and the Preſent</hi> Teſt <hi>in Particular.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Teſt! what's that? 'Tis a <hi>Touch-ſtone</hi> to try what <hi>Metal any</hi> thing is of; and is as neceſſary for <hi>every Man,</hi> every <hi>Houſe-keeper,</hi> every <hi>Body-Politick,</hi> every <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> as is a Touch-ſtone to a <hi>Goldſmith,</hi> there's no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>well</hi> without it.</p>
               <p>A Teſt is of abſolute neceſſity for <hi>every man</hi> always to <hi>carry about</hi> him, to try <hi>himſelf and others;</hi> to try <hi>both</hi> his <hi>own and other</hi> mens Opinions, Words, Works and Ways, whether they be <hi>right;</hi> ſince all is <hi>not Gold</hi> that <hi>glisters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Teſt is neceſſary for every <hi>Houſe-keeper</hi> that wants a <hi>Servant,</hi> a Gueſt, an <hi>Apprentice,</hi> a Journey-man, a <hi>Bayliff,</hi> a Steward, a <hi>Friend,</hi> or the like; for though ſuch a Perſon is recommended, as is <hi>in all things fit</hi> for his turn, except only that he is a <hi>Papist;</hi> (who is obliged to hold (or elſe he is no <hi>Papist</hi>) that the Decrees of <hi>Pope and General Council conjoyn'd</hi> are infallible, and particularly, <hi>that Bloody De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of the Council of Conſtance, that <hi>(nulla fides ſervant cum hereticis) no faith</hi> is to be kept <hi>with a Heretick,</hi> that is, no Faith, Oath, or Promiſe <hi>is binding,</hi> if it be made to <hi>one that is no</hi> Papiſt.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Papists</hi> (like the <hi>Jews,</hi>) (the baſeſt and <hi>moſt inhoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table People under Heaven</hi> (except Papiſts) look upon <hi>all that are not of their Religion,</hi> as Dogs; nay, the <hi>worſt of Dogs,</hi> good for nothing, but to be <hi>proſelyted,</hi> or knockt i'th' head; either <hi>to be turned</hi> to their Religion, or <hi>turned out</hi> of the World; not that <hi>every</hi> Papiſt thinks ſo, but by <hi>their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> they are obliged <hi>ſo to believe.</hi> For which Cauſe <hi>Tacitus</hi> calls the <hi>Jews, erudeliſſima &amp; viliſſima ſervientium pars,</hi> the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62182:9"/>
                  <hi>bloodieſt</hi> and <hi>baſest Slaves</hi> in all the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Jews</hi> Teſt is, Is <hi>be a Jew?</hi> And the Papiſts Teſt (as at this day in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>France</hi>) is ſhortly <hi>this</hi> only, <hi>Is he a Papiſt?</hi> If it be <hi>anſwered</hi> (when cloſeted) <hi>No, no;</hi> then turn <hi>him out;</hi> let him not be truſted, either with <hi>Arms,</hi> a Red coat, or <hi>any Office</hi> of Truſt, or Benefit; bar the Door, <hi>exclude him,</hi> ſhut him out, or <hi>perhaps kill him,</hi> where they are <hi>ſtrong,</hi> and not afraid <hi>of their own</hi> Throats; for if they be <hi>the weaker Party</hi> (as in ſome <hi>Cantons in Switzerland</hi>) there they <hi>are for liberty</hi> of Conſcience; but go but over the next Hills (the <hi>Alps</hi>) into <hi>Piedment,</hi> where the Papiſt is <hi>ten to one,</hi> then, the word is, <hi>(Peter!) kill and eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This makes the World <hi>joyn hands</hi> againſt the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi> either they <hi>totally keep them out</hi> with <hi>Teſts</hi> made for that purpoſe, or confine them to a <hi>certain habit,</hi> or to a certain Street, or Place (as <hi>Dukes-place</hi>) to inhabit; (as we deal with the Feracious and Bloody Tigers and Lyons in the Tower) <hi>keep them</hi> (we do, but) <hi>in a grate;</hi> keep them <hi>faſt,</hi> and have a <hi>watchful eye</hi> over them, <hi>as you love</hi> your lives; for they are <hi>inhoſpitable,</hi> and Common <hi>Enemies to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind;</hi> ſtand <hi>upon your guard</hi> then, keep <hi>off, and out of</hi> their Claws, except you <hi>pare their Nails.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this Cauſe there was ſo many <hi>Penal-Laws and Teſts</hi> made againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in the Reigns of the <hi>four laſt Kings;</hi> (which <hi>(by the way</hi>) has ſinely been <hi>turn'd against Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant-diſſenters,</hi> who were out of theſe Statutes, becauſe <hi>out of the meaning</hi> of thoſe Statutes) oh! the dexterity of a <hi>Jeſuit!</hi> when in <hi>conjunction with</hi> one of his <hi>own</hi> complexion and <hi>face,</hi> ſaving that <hi>this Latter</hi> looks not altogether ſo <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Proteſtant-Perſecutor!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, will ſome ſay, <hi>this preſent Test</hi> (of making all men take the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and certifie the ſame, has done <hi>notable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> againſt the Papiſts, in <hi>theſe</hi> times; and therefore though ſome Diſſenters be kept out for Company, it is <hi>no great</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62182:9"/>
               <p>But <hi>is it lawful then</hi> to do <hi>Evil,</hi> that <hi>Good may come</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? Is not this <hi>that wicked Principle,</hi> that with <hi>one mind and one mouth</hi> we decry and blame in the <hi>Jeſuit?</hi> Or is it lawful to maintain our Religion or Church by <hi>prophane-means,</hi> and by mocking of God? Who would not <hi>hate</hi> a Religion and Church, that <hi>cannot be kept up</hi> without blaſphemy, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful methods?</p>
               <p>But, will ſome ſay, <hi>God forbid!</hi> We never <hi>did,</hi> nor <hi>ever will keep up</hi> a Church by ſuch ungodlineſs: Then liſten, what <hi>we have done already</hi> in impoſing this ſaid <hi>Preſent Teſt,</hi> of making an <hi>Earthly</hi> Door, or Political <hi>Door-bar</hi> of the Holy, <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and Heavenly <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Preſent Teſt</hi> is the more <hi>ſuſpiciouſly Profane,</hi> and to be abominated by all <hi>true</hi> Chriſtians, becauſe it is ſaid to be <hi>the Project</hi> of a <hi>Polititian,</hi> that was always reckon'd to have more <hi>wit</hi> than <hi>grace;</hi> more of <hi>Machiavel</hi> than of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And who made <hi>Religion</hi> and the bleſſed Sacraments <hi>Politick-tools,</hi> and that was <hi>all,</hi> at leaſt the <hi>chief uſe</hi> he made of Religion, and ſaid (if he be not belied, that) <hi>That was all that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was good for;</hi> well ſaid <hi>Machiavel!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A more <hi>undoubted inſtance</hi> of his Profaneſs cannot <hi>Well</hi> be given, than in this preſent <hi>Teſt;</hi> Is it not profane, and moſt abominable, if the Learned and Pious <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tus</hi> and Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> and other Interpreters of <hi>greatest vogue</hi> amongſt us, do give us <hi>the true,</hi> genuine, <hi>rational</hi> and pious meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in their <hi>Comments</hi> upon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. ſaying, <hi>That to eat and drink unworthily (anaxios)</hi> is to eat and drink <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſutably or unmeetly to the end, deſign</hi> and Inſtitution of the <hi>Bleſſed Sacrament;</hi> (ſo we are commanded to walk <hi>worthy (axios) of the Goſpel,</hi> that is <hi>ſutably to the Goſpel;</hi>) Then he that eateth and drinketh <hi>unmeetly,</hi> namely, <hi>to the end</hi> and Inſtitution of the Sacrament (not that he may <hi>get Chriſt,</hi> but a <hi>Gown,</hi> a Sword, <hi>a Place</hi> or Preferment, making <hi>a Test</hi> of the Bleſſed Sacrament, making <hi>Chriſt</hi> (who is the only
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62182:10"/>
                  <hi>Door</hi> and the only <hi>Way</hi> to High-places in <hi>Heaven,</hi> the only <hi>Door</hi> to High-places on <hi>Earth,</hi> making the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> the only way to fill the lean Bellies of a Man and his Family <hi>with Bakers Bread; He that Eateth and Drinketh thus unmeet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Eateth and Drinketh his own Damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſad Choice, to <hi>Starve here,</hi> or be <hi>Damn'd hereafter;</hi> nay, ſome that have often <hi>taken it worthily</hi> or <hi>meetly,</hi> are not always fit in <hi>Three Months</hi> to take it <hi>Worthily,</hi> then take your choice to <hi>Starve</hi> or be <hi>Damn'd:</hi> What a <hi>Temptation</hi> is here to damn even a <hi>Conformiſt?</hi> What a Temptation to <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, Atheiſm,</hi> and <hi>mocking</hi> of God? Is not this as bold a <hi>Stinting</hi> the Grace of God, to <hi>come</hi> within three Months time? Juſt like the Canon that enjoyns the Sacrament— However at <hi>Eaſter?</hi> What fit or unfit? <hi>What</hi> right or wrong? Yes, ſtarve in a Goal, or <hi>Eat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> your own <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> Oh! Abomination in a <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſtians! Nay a <hi>Church</hi> of Proteſtants, and a Proteſtant Nation! Have we not ſtill (as we <hi>formerly had</hi>) ſome (<hi>Quid pro quo's,</hi> amongſt us) Papiſts in <hi>Maſquerade?</hi> Papiſts with a <hi>Protestant Vizor,</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi>'s Vizor on? Turn up his <hi>Maſque,</hi> let us ſee. But <hi>God will not</hi> (long) be <hi>mocked</hi> with Political Tricks? It is dangerous <hi>Playing</hi> our Politick Pranks with <hi>Edge-Tools:</hi> And is there no way to bar the Earthly <hi>Doors,</hi> but with Heavenly <hi>Edge-Tools?</hi> Have a care of cutting thy Fingers, <hi>Machiavel!</hi> Muſt the Laws made againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be made of uſe againſt <hi>Protestant Recuſants,</hi> who are out of the Reaſon of them?</p>
               <p>But can any Nation ſubſiſt without <hi>a Teſt,</hi> a <hi>Fence,</hi> and a <hi>Barr'd Door</hi> to keep out the common Enemy thereof?</p>
               <p>No, I anſwer, <hi>No;</hi> There's none but <hi>Fools</hi> will neglect their <hi>Fence:</hi> But the <hi>Oath of Supremacy</hi> (a long-try'd and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd Teſt, and making the Declaration againſt <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> enjoyned 25 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. c 2. &amp; 30 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. c. 2.) has and will do <hi>that Feat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh! But <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> then will come in; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62182:10"/>get their <hi>Birth-Rights</hi> in Church and State <hi>as well as we:</hi> Surely there is a way to bar the Door againſt our Enemies, and yet let in our Friends; except we think the Houſe will not hold us all, or (rather) not feed us all. Ay! Is <hi>that</hi> it? If it pinch <hi>there,</hi> Zeal againſt Popery is but a <hi>Sconce,</hi> and a <hi>Vizard</hi> drawn over the <hi>ugly Face</hi> of Covetouſneſs and Self-ends. When Boys are ſcrambling in a Room for Nuts and Apples, thoſe that are in Poſſeſſion, and upon the Place, and got in, will be ſure to <hi>Bar the Doors</hi> and keep out others, eſpecially ſuch as are active and <hi>nimbler</hi> than themſelves; Ay, <hi>they are the Wiſer,</hi> you'll ſay.</p>
               <p>But where's the <hi>Honesty</hi> all this while? <hi>Where</hi>'s the <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> Nay, where's the <hi>Wiſdom?</hi> And where's the <hi>Policy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if the lucky <hi>Scramblers</hi> be beſet, or <hi>ſet upon,</hi> with bloody High-way-men, as they carry away their <hi>Booty;</hi> would they not be glad that <hi>thoſe they barr'd out,</hi> ſhould aſſiſt them? <hi>Yes ſurely,</hi> for who ever denied a <hi>Diſſenter</hi> the Peril, the Hazard and the Pains, ſo that we go away with the <hi>Gains?</hi> But is there any Equity or Conſcience in all this? Has not a certain Nation <hi>(in our Time)</hi> been hazarded a <hi>Third Time,</hi> by Patriots that have been <hi>Priest-ridden;</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotted and <hi>Nuzled to maintain Prieſt-Craft,</hi> and Compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in Religion? <hi>Who</hi> diſlikes it? But how? VVhat upon Compulſion? Uniformity by force of Arms? It has been found an Idle, Vain, VVicked, Bloody, Bigotted <hi>Popiſh,</hi> Antichriſtian, and <hi>Impoſſible Attempt,</hi> in all Ages, in all Nations. The old Rule was, <hi>In Neceſſariis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas, in Adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphoris Libertas, in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trijſque Charitas;</hi> Unity in things <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,</hi> Liberty in <hi>Indifferent</hi> Things, in <hi>Both</hi> Charity.</p>
               <p>For 'till all men be of <hi>one ſize,</hi> one feature, one <hi>complexion</hi> and <hi>face,</hi> 'tis impoſſible they ſhould be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform;</hi> nay, God and Nature ſeem to delight in <hi>Variety:</hi> But vain man, <hi>mad with ſelf-love,</hi> Opinionatry and <hi>Bigotiſm,</hi> would <hi>compel all men</hi> to be of his own Dimenſions and Attainments, whereas there
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62182:11"/>are ſcarce two Men to be found in the VVorld <hi>alike.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Folly</hi> proceeds from a <hi>Vulgar Error</hi> that <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ops</hi> have Eſpous'd, namely, that there can be no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> without <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity;</hi> and when they pray to God, <hi>(as they ought)</hi> to make us all of one Mind, and one Mouth; if by one <hi>Mouth,</hi> they mean <hi>their own</hi> Mouth, then they are <hi>Bigotted</hi> with an Opinion of their <hi>own Infallibity,</hi> and are <hi>no Church-of-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland-Men</hi> in that particular.</p>
               <p>Alas, alas, we are commanded <hi>to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the Bond of Peace,</hi> but that may be done <hi>without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity;</hi> there is ſcarcely two Brethren in the World <hi>alike</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform,</hi> yet they may <hi>live in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and love</hi> like Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
               <p>Can men be wiſe that value the keeping of their <hi>Trinckets</hi> above their <hi>Lives,</hi> and above the Peace and <hi>Welfare of the Church</hi> and Proteſtant Religion? And why ſhould not a <hi>Proteſtant Church</hi> be as large and wide as to hold all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come,</hi> come; <hi>let them have a Care</hi> that they do not hold <hi>up the Price</hi> of their Trinckets at too dear a rate; leſt they <hi>ſlip their Market,</hi> and be glad to part with them e'er long, for an <hi>Old Song;</hi> and ſeriouſly read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. from <hi>Verſe</hi> 4. to <hi>Verſe</hi> 15. Bleſs us! Cannot men <hi>live and let live,</hi> (even) let thoſe live that have not ſo many Brains, nor ſo good Eyes as themſelves? Though they are not <hi>one Mouth</hi> with you, nor ſo wide a Mouth and Swallow, they are as <hi>God made them</hi> as well as you; and though they <hi>ſee not ſo well</hi> as they ſhould, they ſee as <hi>well as they can;</hi> to their own <hi>Maſter they ſtand and fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What <hi>Rational Man</hi> in the World (if his Reaſon be <hi>Judge,</hi> and not Dethron'd and Depos'd; Benighted and Eclipſed with Paſſion, Self-intereſt, Self-conceit, and the like) but muſt ſay. <hi>That it is very meet that we ſhould do to others, as we would that others in like Circumstances ſhould do to us?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62182:11"/>
               <p>'Tis poſſible (for what has been may be again) that the <hi>Old Test</hi> may be (many Ages hence) <hi>Renewed,</hi> (which <hi>bar'd</hi> the Church Doors, and the Doors of Preſerment in Church and State, <hi>Excluding all</hi> from being Church-men, Judges, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, Mayors, Aldermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that would not leave worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God according to the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book;</hi> wouldſt not thou <hi>(thou Weapon'd-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity Bigot!)</hi> Exclaim (at leaſt grumble) <hi>at ſuch a Teſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But with what <hi>reaſon</hi> canſt thou grumble? Except thou conclude, that Church of <hi>England</hi> is infallible, (in ſpight of her own 39 <hi>Articles</hi> to the contrary) or, except thou art not content to take ſuch meaſure as now thou meteſt to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that are as <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> as thy ſelf: Where is the Juſtice of ſuch Grumbling? Thou art for Uniformity, one Mind and one Mouth, ſo are all <hi>Rational</hi> Men; but thou art alſo for <hi>Weapon'd</hi> Uniformity, that's unreaſonable and unſcriptural, and unapoſtolical; and alſo becauſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther little thing (called) <hi>Impoſſibility:</hi> It is not to be done by Sword or Gun, <hi>Teſts or Penal Laws.</hi> Have we not been trying Concluſions and Experiments about it in <hi>the Body Politick,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, even to the <hi>Conſumption</hi> of the Body Politicks? And who has got any thing by it, ſaving a few <hi>Priests?</hi> But we muſt always be tampering with ungodly, unreaſonable and Antichriſtian <hi>Phyſick,</hi> only to enrich the Phyſitian, and <hi>keep up his Practice,</hi> and his Hand in Ure; Do we de claim againſt <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> and Tyranny, and yet ſuffer ſuch <hi>Teſts</hi> to take away our Birth-rights? Queen <hi>Maries Fives</hi> conſum'd the Heats between <hi>Con</hi> and <hi>Noncon!</hi> when in Priſon together, they ſhook Hands and were <hi>Friends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ay, ſays <hi>Bigot,</hi> moſt true; therefore we would have them like us. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform and of one Mouth,</hi> meaning, that every Mouth ſhould be alike, and one with his <hi>Wide Mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe that <hi>Little Mouth</hi> (let that be his Name) ſtretches, and <hi>stretches his Mouth,</hi> that ſo it may be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform,</hi> and like to Great Mouth, and cannot do it for his <hi>Heart and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62182:12"/>Blood:</hi> (by Scripture-Rule, <hi>He that is ſtrong ſhould ſtoop, and bear the Infirmities of the weak,</hi> and condeſcend (and to keep my Allegory) <hi>Wide Mouth</hi> ſhould meet <hi>Little Mouth</hi> half way, contracting his large <hi>Gape and Swallow,</hi> that ſo they may be of one <hi>Mouth</hi>) But what cares ſome Men for Scripture?</p>
               <p>If that will not do, what do you ſay to <hi>Reaſon?</hi> Is it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that if Little <hi>Mouth</hi> ſhould happen to get into the Saddle, and get the <hi>Staff in his Hand,</hi> (and thou be diſmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> wilful, and un-ſcriptural, and unreaſonable Impoſitions and Oppreſſions, wouldſt thou think it reaſonable) that he ſhould pare and cut, and pinch thy <hi>Wade Mouth,</hi> to the ſcantling of his <hi>Narrow Chaps?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If not, then <hi>out of thine own (Wide) mouth will I judge thee, thou wicked Servant!</hi> Shouldſt not thou have <hi>Compaſſion</hi> on thy Fellow-ſervant, (like thy ſelf, erroneous) as thou wouldſt have <hi>him,</hi> or Almighty God, have <hi>Pity on thee?</hi> To our Comfort God ſeeth; and he that is <hi>higher than the Higheſt,</hi> regardeth, and there are Higher than they, Eccleſ. 5.8.</p>
               <p>But will ſome ſay, though it be a <hi>Teſt</hi> ſuſpiciouſly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, (if any Holy thing in the World can be prophan'd) by making <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>Sacraments</hi> (the moſt <hi>Venerable and Sacred</hi> of all the Parts or Offices in Religion) Tools and Tricks of <hi>State;</hi> yet this <hi>Teſt</hi> has done good Service againſt the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> the irreconcileable Enemies of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: It has kept out the Papiſt from Offices in Church and State, Navy and Army.</p>
               <p>Never, (I anſwer) it never did keep out any <hi>Papist,</hi> nor any but Diſſenters; yet if all this ſhould be as true, as it is evidently falſe, yet this <hi>Teſt</hi> is not juſtifiable, becauſe we may not lay an evident <hi>Temptation</hi> of ſtumbling in our Brothers way, to make him fall; nor do <hi>Evil</hi> that good may come thereon; (as aforeſaid) nor thus <hi>keep up Gods Church?</hi> What is the bringing <hi>the Abomination of Deſolation into the Holy Place,</hi> but making Holy things, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62182:12"/>a <hi>Drudge</hi> and Slave to <hi>Machiavel?</hi> (O Prophanation abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable!) Muſt the bleſſed Sacrament of Divine Love, his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution (made on purpoſe to Incorporate us with him, and one with another in Divine Love) be the only <hi>Entrance</hi> and means to let us in to a Body Politick or Corporation, or <hi>into the Door</hi> of Preferment? <hi>Sacra Sacris, &amp; Sacri Sacris,</hi> was the Old Rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> may make a man <hi>unfit</hi> to be employed in the <hi>State;</hi> but is it not <hi>prophane</hi> to make the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a <hi>Political Engine</hi> or Qualification, to <hi>let a Man</hi> into Money and <hi>Mammon;</hi> but we cannot thus ſerve two Maſters, (<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Mammon.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Beſides, I deny, that this <hi>Teſt of the Sacrament</hi> did any good at any time, in keeping <hi>ſo much as one Papist out</hi> of any Office, Employment or Preferment, either in <hi>Church or State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if this be <hi>true,</hi> then <hi>Hatred</hi> againſt <hi>Popery</hi> is but a <hi>Colour</hi> wherewith Hypocriſie <hi>paints</hi> the <hi>ugly Face and Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> of Hatred and Malice againſt Diſſenters, (that have <hi>not ſo wide a Swallow</hi> as themſelves) with the <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> and <hi>Zeal againſt Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Otherwiſe, why did this <hi>Teſt-Bill</hi> paſs ſo readily, and the <hi>Excluſion-Bill</hi> thrown out without a Conference, which is not uſual? There may be many good Reaſons, which I will not now inquire into. But was it Loyalty and a <hi>Religious Awe,</hi> to hurt no man in his Goods and <hi>Birth right upon the ſcore of Religion?</hi> That's <hi>impoſſible to be a Reaſon</hi> that prevailed with thoſe <hi>Lords and Gentlemen</hi> that ſtood to their <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> till the King was diveſted of both, which are <hi>His Birth-Right now</hi> (at this day) as much, nay, <hi>more</hi> than at <hi>the time</hi> of the <hi>Excluſion-Bill:</hi> (for no man that <hi>ſpoke beſt, and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> the Excluſion-Bill, did touch <hi>upon that String,</hi> namely, that the <hi>King and Parliament cannot diſpoſe of the Crown of</hi> England; (for fear (I ſupoſe) of the Penalty mentioned in the Statute of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to that purpoſe;) And to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62182:13"/>repeat the words of that moſt <hi>Excellent Speaker</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Commons; If there were a Lyon in the Lobby,</hi> ſhall it be <hi>still a Queſtion amongſt Wiſe men, Whether</hi> it were better to <hi>keep him out,</hi> (now he is <hi>out,</hi>) or to open the Door and <hi>let him in,</hi> and then <hi>bind</hi> him?</p>
               <p>Some wiſe men <hi>choſe the latter,</hi> and if God had not been miraculouſly kind to us (to ſhow his Grace and Finger) when ſome thought we had neglected the means, if the Lion had <hi>prov'd a Rampant Lion,</hi> or had had a <hi>Lion</hi>'s <hi>Heart,</hi> and the <hi>Cruelty of a Lion,</hi> there might have been <hi>Scratching Work;</hi> and Thouſands had (e'er this) followed thoſe (otherwiſe) <hi>Incomparable Patriots, Eſſex, Ruſſel, Sidney,</hi> and <hi>Corniſh,</hi> &amp;c. for who has not had a <hi>Hand upon his Hilt,</hi> to <hi>Fight the King's Guards,</hi> (his <hi>Iriſh</hi> Souldiers) when the word was, They <hi>are a coming?</hi> VVhereas the Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> was condemn'd for being <hi>only in the Room,</hi> where there was ſome diſcourſe of Surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Kings Guards. But we muſt leave theſe things to him that <hi>judgeth Righteouſly;</hi> The Iniquity of the <hi>Amorites</hi> was not then full: Popery was not drunk enough with Blood. The Papiſts have for a hundred years laſt paſt, been kept out of the Government, and have been Exluded all Offices Eccleſiaſtical, Civil and Military, by that <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Honeſt Teſt,</hi> (namely, <hi>in Renouncing the Pope and all his Evil Works,</hi> by the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> which our preſent King (King <hi>James</hi> II.) by his <hi>Diſpenſing Power</hi> vacated, in the firſt place, as being a <hi>Long-approved</hi> and ſufficient Bar and Bulwark to keep out Popery in the four laſt preceding Reigns. It is alſo as true, that as he left <hi>no ſtone unturn'd</hi> that lay in the way of bringing in Popery, ſo <hi>he was neceſſitatid</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (alſo) to ſet aſide and diſponce with this <hi>New Teſt,</hi> which did inflict grievous Penalties upon them that <hi>durst</hi> or <hi>did</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in, <hi>without taking it:</hi> But, they had <hi>all been kept out</hi> to this day, and <hi>were kept out</hi> an hundred years <hi>before,</hi> and <hi>could not</hi> therefore <hi>need</hi> his Diſpenſing Power, until he let them in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62182:13"/>(two years before) by Diſpenſing with the Oath of <hi>Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> A Teſt, that perhaps had been <hi>ſtill thought</hi> ſufficient, if this <hi>Teſt</hi> had not jumpt right with ſome men's Malice, that hated <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> as much, <hi>if not more</hi> than <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed I grant, That the King by that Gracious Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, gain'd the Diſſenters, and thereby <hi>lost</hi> the Love of <hi>High-Church-men,</hi> who were as <hi>quiet</hi> and gentle as Lambs, and Loyal as <hi>Heart could wiſh,</hi> when he <hi>diſpenc'd with</hi> that great and approved <hi>Teſt,</hi> the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> (for two long years together) whilſt he permitted them, and <hi>maintain'd them</hi> and their <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt Diſſenters.</p>
               <p>But when he put out his Declaration for <hi>Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> (the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> that God (the only <hi>King</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences) has given to all Mankind) would ſome Men ſo <hi>much as read the Indulgence,</hi> which His Majeſty (the <hi>best Act</hi> that <hi>ever he did</hi> in his Life) both in Piety, (and Policy too; for it has been the Life of Trade in <hi>Holland,</hi> and the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> (or Inquiſition,) their Diſ-peopling, and Deſtruction of Trade and Riches in <hi>Flanders,</hi>) as God's Deputy Re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd and <hi>Ordain'd?</hi> No, no! Though expreſly enjoyn'd in the Rubrick of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Books!</hi> What Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? What <hi>Bandying</hi> againſt it? And perhaps for good Reaſons: But have they ſcrupled to read (and make Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for) worſe things (that I ſay not) Impoſtures? Or, was it <hi>becauſe it was Evil,</hi> as to the <hi>Matter?</hi> None <hi>had the Face</hi> to ſay <hi>ſo:</hi> But, Evil as to the Form of Diſpenſing, becauſe <hi>not done in Form of Law;</hi> namely, not Repealed by the ſame Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that <hi>Enacted</hi> it; which Reaſon, <hi>perhaps is a good</hi> Reaſon, but how could it be <hi>more a Reaſon now</hi> in this Caſe, then it was when he <hi>Diſpenc'd with the Oath of Supremacy?</hi> Which was as <hi>much againſt Law</hi> as this Diſpenſation; and yet, whilſt he <hi>maintain'd</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Proſecute Diſſenters</hi> with their Excommunications, Capias's, Fines
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62182:14"/>and Impriſonments; they were huſh'd, and <hi>Serene,</hi> and as loyal as <hi>could be,</hi> Preaching up <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> (Prayers and Tears) as the <hi>only Weapons</hi> of a Chriſtian, Groaning under the Oppreſſion of <hi>Superiours,</hi> during all <hi>the long time</hi> that they were <hi>uppermoſt,</hi> and felt no <hi>Smart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Patriarch of Conſtantinople</hi> is as great an Enemy to Popery, as any Prelate or Lay-man amongſt us; yet he holds more ridiculous and <hi>unaccountable</hi> Errors than the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> and enſlaves the poor <hi>Greeks</hi> as tyrannically, as the <hi>Pope</hi> does enſlave his <hi>Italian</hi> Papiſts? What are the <hi>poor Greeks</hi> the better for this <hi>Bulwark</hi> againſt the Pope and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery? The <hi>Patriarch ſcornes</hi> to kiſs the <hi>Pope's Toe,</hi> and to be <hi>Tenant at will</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> or to hold his <hi>Patriarchate</hi> of him, or under <hi>him,</hi> and Preaches and Writes againſt <hi>Popiſh Errors,</hi> but holds the poor <hi>Greeks to as bad Errors:</hi> And is not the <hi>Pope on the other ſide the Water,</hi> as Fierce, Dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and Pragmatical a Bigot, in forcing the poor <hi>Greeks to believe as he believes,</hi> and to be as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformable</hi> and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to his <hi>Trinckets</hi> and Ceremonies, as the <hi>Pope</hi> (with his <hi>Inquiſition</hi>) in <hi>Italy?</hi> What good does <hi>Graecia</hi> get <hi>by ſuch a Bulwark</hi> againſt Popery, when Pope and Popery cannot poſſibly make <hi>their Condition much worſe</hi> then it is? A true <hi>Chriſtian Protestant</hi> ſhould proteſt againſt, and abominate <hi>Popery of the New,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Old Edition;</hi> and ſhould keep cloſe to the Apoſtolical and <hi>Primitive Rule of Charity,</hi> in eaſe of Nonconformity.</p>
               <p>There were <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in the Church of <hi>Philippi, (as now amongst us)</hi> ſo many <hi>Men,</hi> to many different <hi>Minds;</hi> ſo many <hi>Men,</hi> ſo many different <hi>Features,</hi> perhaps in doubtful Matters of Faith; and ſome had better Eyes and Brains, Hearts and Legs, than others; and therefore had different Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Opinions and <hi>Attainments:</hi> Now, <hi>What ſhall be done</hi> in this Caſe, was the Queſtion? All <hi>preſt forward towards</hi> the <hi>Mark</hi> of the Prize of the <hi>High-Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62182:14"/>Phil. 3.14. But ſome <hi>lagg'd behind,</hi> as is uſual in a <hi>Race;</hi> (to which the Apoſtle aludes <hi>Ver.</hi> 13.) Now the Queſtion is, VVhat ſhould be done <hi>with theſe that lagg'd behind, and cannot come up ſo near the Mark as we?</hi> Burn them, Conſume them with Fire from Heaven or Earth, (ſays zealous <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi>) and the <hi>Papists;</hi> Or, ſhall we <hi>ſpur them up</hi> with <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> or Excommunicate them, and then Goal them? No; <hi>Ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: And St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 15th verſe of that <hi>3d</hi> Chapter of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians; If any Man be otherwiſe minded,</hi> (or be a Diſſenter, of another Opinion, then make uſe, of what Remedy? Of your VVrath? Your Paſſion? Your <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests?</hi> No, no; wait God's Leiſure; make uſe of your Charity, rather than <hi>Wrath;</hi> of your Patience, rather than Paſſion; leave him to the <hi>King, to whom alone Conſcience</hi> belongs; for if any man be a <hi>Nonconformist,</hi> or otherwiſe minded) <hi>God ſhall Reveal even this unto him:</hi> He did not bid them (do, as ſome ſpiritual <hi>Watchmen</hi> now do,) call the <hi>Corporal,</hi> call the <hi>Conſtable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that indeed, <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> weapons and <hi>Christ</hi>'s weapons are vaſtly <hi>different,</hi> quite of <hi>another</hi> Shape, Form, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and made of quite <hi>contrary Stuff</hi> and Matter.</p>
               <p>Chriſt and his Holy Apoſtles converted the <hi>World, not with Earthly,</hi> Carnal, and Political <hi>Tests</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> and are <hi>we Wiſer</hi> than they? Did they borrow any of the <hi>Magiſtrates Weapons,</hi> or <hi>Weapons</hi> (like <hi>Mabomet</hi>) from the Arms of Fleſh? No, they are <hi>purely Spiritual,</hi> Heavenly and Divine.</p>
               <p>God did forbid (in the <hi>Old Law</hi>) the <hi>wearing of Lindſey-Wolſey;</hi> or the yoaking of an <hi>Ox and an Aſs together,</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Myſtery: <hi>Almighty God and Chriſt</hi> (under the Goſpel eſpecially) <hi>hating the Chaos</hi> of mingling <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> jumbling carnal and ſpiritual Tools in <hi>Hodge-podge;</hi> they will <hi>not mingle will,</hi> they cannot poſſibly Incorporate, nor carry on one main End, and <hi>one onely Deſign.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62182:15"/>
               <p>For, if <hi>ye have bitter Envying and Strife in your Hearts</hi> (ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with carnal Tools, carnal VVeapons, carnal Laws, and carnal Teſts,) this VViſdom deſcendeth <hi>not from above,</hi> but is (fetch'd from Hell, and is therefore) <hi>Earthly, Senſual, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Wiſdom that is from above, is first pure,</hi> (ſo ſhould the Holy Sacraments be pure, and unmix'd with carnal Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices) then <hi>Peaceable, Gentle, and eaſie to be intreated,</hi> &amp;c. (binding men to the Peace and good Behaviour, not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to ſtickle with carnal VVeapons againſt Men of <hi>different Opinions</hi> in matters of meer Religion) but comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us, <hi>if poſſible, and as much as lieth in us, to live peaceably with all men;</hi> ſurely it is poſſible, nay eaſie in this Caſe, moſt eaſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All?</hi> Yes; if they be <hi>Men,</hi> our Brethren (as being <hi>Sons of Adam</hi>) though <hi>not of our Religion,</hi> nor of our ſize and pitch, nor of our Features and Complexion, though of <hi>different Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> or of no <hi>Religion,</hi> yet they are <hi>Men;</hi> (and where God makes no Exception, how dare we make Exceptions?) Since we are obliged to have a <hi>Charity as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal as Mankind,</hi> and to live peaceably with all men?</p>
               <p>If this be Goſpel, what becomes of our Teſts and Penal Laws? All our Lawyers are agreed, that all <hi>Statutes</hi> are Null and <hi>Ipſo facto, void in themſelves,</hi> if they be <hi>contrary</hi> to the Laws of God, and Laws of Nature, or Right Reaſon.</p>
               <p>And <hi>this preſent Teſt</hi> (though Enacted by ten thouſand Parliaments) is never the more juſtifiable, becauſe it is a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Temptation</hi> even to Conformiſts, <hi>(ſometimes,)</hi> and to Nonconformiſts <hi>at all times,</hi> to take their choice, (chuſe them whether,) either to <hi>starve here,</hi> or (at leaſt) <hi>be kept out of their Birth-rights as men and Chriſtians;</hi> or elſe, to Eat and Drink it unmeetly, to the Holy End, Deſign, and Inſtitution of that bleſſed Sacrament; (which was not Political, Carnal, and <hi>Worldly,</hi> but Pure, Spiritual, Heavenly and Divine; and therefore to Eat and Drink, for a <hi>Political Test, and State-Policy,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62182:15"/>is to Eat and Drink it <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthily and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmeetly;</hi> and therefore Men <hi>ſo Eating and Drinking it, Eat and Drink their own Damnation.</hi> Away with it <hi>for Shame!</hi> Let it not be ſuch <hi>a Scandal to our Holy Protestant Religion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>Of</hi> Penal Laws <hi>in Matters of meer</hi> Religion.</head>
               <p>MAny people cry up the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and <hi>drink healths</hi> to the Proſperity of the Church of <hi>England!</hi> And yet neither know <hi>what makes</hi> a true Church of Chriſt, nor <hi>who are this ſame thing</hi> (of ſome mens <hi>making</hi> or <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi>) called <hi>the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What conſtitutes a true Church but <hi>true Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>true Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raments,</hi> according to plain Scriptures? The <hi>Diſcipline</hi> is left to diſcretion. For, I ſuppoſe we are all agreed, that <hi>this or that form</hi> of Church Government, is not <hi>Jure Divino.</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> I. (a great <hi>Epiſcopal-man</hi>) yet denied that <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (as we have them)</hi> are <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> (other than as Prieſts, or <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> are one and the ſame thing, and undiſtinguiſhed in many places of <hi>Scripture;</hi> but yet that wiſe King held them, <hi>not</hi> to be <hi>contra jus Divinum, not contrary to</hi> Gods Law, that is (I ſuppoſe) <hi>when</hi> they feed the Flocks, not Lording it over God's Heritage, as if they had <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over our Faith</hi> (which even the Apoſtles renounc'd) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing what they believe, and their attainments, upon us to believe, whether we can or no, or elſe Anathematize, Goal, and Impriſon them, and lot them lye there till they ſtarve and dye: What comfort is it <hi>with ſo much ſtrugling</hi> to keep out an <hi>Italian Biſhop,</hi> Romiſh cruelty, Fire and Faggot (that ſoon diſpatches men out of their pain,) and ſtill to keep <hi>ſomething like it:</hi> Nay, a worſe, if to lye in Priſon (after Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication) and there to ſtarve and dye a lingring death,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62182:16"/>(like Crucifixion) feeling a thouſand deaths, he and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and all this for not paying the Regiſter, or taking the Church-wardens Oath, or the Holy Sacrament at <hi>Eaſter;</hi> neither of which the perſons durſt do for fear of Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Then take your choice, Death or Damnation, a lingring Death, Crucifying them, and making them and their poor Families feel many deaths; And is this amendment? I hope our Biſhops will <hi>now recant</hi> theſe violent and carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, ſince ſeveral of them <hi>have done</hi> it already, promiſing to be willing to <hi>come to a temper</hi> (in their Petition to the King) And thereby confeſſing that they had been too hot and diſtempered before; and yet <hi>even, at this day</hi> I am afraid, that ſome men are only againſt <hi>Carnal Weapons, Prophane-Teſts</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> not becauſe they <hi>like them not,</hi> but becauſe they ſee <hi>they cannot</hi> hold them; the Genius of the Nation being univerſally againſt ſuch a Wild-fire Church.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> defind all carnal Weapons in his Spiritual War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: <hi>The Weapons of our Warfare are not Carnal but Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed he <hi>ſtood up ſtoutly</hi> in defence of the Priviledge of his <hi>Birth-Right,</hi> when that was invaded by <hi>Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> Tyranny and Oppreſſion; and therefore, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſent for an honeſt <hi>General and his Army,</hi> to come to his Reſcue; and his Excellency, <hi>Claudius Lycias</hi> (after St. <hi>Paul</hi> had given him to underſtand that <hi>he was a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and wrong'd of his <hi>Birth-right</hi>) <hi>came with an Army</hi> and delivered him out of the hands of his Oppreſſors, having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the matter of wrong. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.27. <hi>Act.</hi> 22.29.</p>
               <p>Then good night, Church of <hi>England,</hi> if the Jaylor do not help it, will ſome ſay; and ſo ſay I, good night! And hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to her and long life; for <hi>the Gates</hi> of Hell <hi>(Hadou, of the Grave)</hi> ſhall never prevail againſt the true Church; that is, the Church ſhall never have a <hi>Grave, it ſhall never dye,</hi> but to the Worlds end, there ſhall be ſome always that believe in, and confeſs the Lord Jeſus, Son of the living God.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62182:16"/>
               <p>The Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (which is Confirm'd by Act of Parliament) is contained in the <hi>Comman Prayer-Book,</hi> and alſo in the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> and in the <hi>Homilies</hi> that are ſet out, or ſhall be ſet out by Authority.</p>
               <p>This <hi>laſt is a deep one,</hi> He muſt have a <hi>wide Swallow</hi> that has an implicit Faith and <hi>believes as the Church believes;</hi> when that ſame Church in whom he doth believe, <hi>confeſſeth the truth,</hi> namely, that <hi>ſhe may Err,</hi> or teach what is <hi>not truth?</hi> Now would I in all Humility and Modeſty <hi>put this ſober Query,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query</hi> 1. How can a Man ſubſcribe to the Doctrine in Homilies <hi>that ſhall</hi> be put out (except he have a Popiſh Implicit Faith, to believe as the Church believes) <hi>before he knows what</hi> Doctrinal Homilies Authority will put forth? And ſuch Authority that has perhaps <hi>Err'd</hi> in Doctrinal points already put forth by Authority, or by their own Confeſſion, <hi>may Err.</hi> as well as the Church of <hi>Rome, Antioch, Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> that have Err'd already, as the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> ingeniouſly and modeſtly confeſs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query</hi> 2. It is worth a modeſt Inquiry, and now <hi>moſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> to Inquire (<hi>now I ſay,</hi> when things are come to a full ſtop, and in the faireſt and moſt probable way to <hi>ſettle upon a laſting</hi> Foundation) Is it <hi>now high time</hi> modeſtly to Inquire, who is the Judge of matters of Faith which all Chriſtian Proteſtants (<hi>a new Name only for the old Apostolical</hi> and Primitive Chriſtian) ought to obey in pain of <hi>the Jayle h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re,</hi> and <hi>Damnation</hi> hereafter, if he <hi>perſiſt in his Diſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt</hi> and Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity thereunto; though <hi>ſome Bigots</hi> call it a <hi>wicked Error.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a ſawcy Queſtion, will ſome ſay: But (I Anſwer) that he <hi>that ſays</hi> ſo, is an <hi>Impudent Blaſphemer againſt the holy Ghoſt:</hi> whom, I only Eccho, for the holy Ghoſt, by the holy Apoſtle (St. <hi>Paul</hi>) puts this very Queſtion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Who art thou that Judgeſt another Man's Servant? To his own Master he ſtandeth or falleth: Yea, he ſhall be holden up, for God is able to make him ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62182:17"/>
               <p>Then from that 4th Verſe, the Apoſtle proceeds to ſtate <hi>ſome caſes,</hi> wherein Chriſtians were <hi>not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform, neither need<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to be</hi> Uniform, as being therein a <hi>Royal Priesthood, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged Kings,</hi> exempt <hi>from humane Puniſhment, Judgment, Impoſitions, Correction,</hi> or <hi>Condemnation,</hi> as being <hi>accountable</hi> for their Opinions finally <hi>to God only, Rom.</hi> 14.11.</p>
               <p>Whence <hi>he Concludes</hi> with this <hi>Apoſtolical Canon</hi> (that to all intents and purpoſes, <hi>repeals,</hi> makes void, and diſanulls <hi>all humane Canons,</hi> Impoſitions or Acts of Uniformity in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith, or in Impoſing their own Attainments and Creeds upon all others) ſaying, <hi>Let us not therefore Judge one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any more, but judge rather that no man put a Stumbling-Block</hi> (Scandal) <hi>or occaſion to fall in his Brothers way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1. But let the <hi>Strong bear the Infirmities of the Weak, and not pleaſe themſelves;</hi> with their own Bigoted Notions, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heavy burdens, and grievous to be born, which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (in their Sins of Commiſſion without Rule, Wilfull, Idle and unaccountable Ceremonies) will <hi>not touch with one of their Fingers:</hi> But is <hi>there any Conſcience</hi> that the <hi>Weak ſhould bear</hi> the Infirmities <hi>of the ſtrong?</hi> In Defiance and <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter</hi> to that ſaid Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1.</p>
               <p>From all which Premiſes does it not <hi>clearly follow,</hi> and may we not <hi>Conclude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concluſion</hi> I. 1. That <hi>God is the only King</hi> of Conſciences, as King <hi>Charles</hi> I. of Pious Memory concludes, ſaying, <hi>Who am I, (Eik. Baſil.) that I ſhould Invade God's Throne,</hi> the <hi>only King</hi> of Conſciences?</p>
               <p>Wherefore did <hi>Lucifer</hi> become a Devil? He aſpir'd to God's Throne, and would be like him.</p>
               <p>Wherefore is <hi>that Wicked</hi> Wretch (in 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.) that <hi>muſt and ſhall</hi> fall) called the <hi>Man of Sin?</hi> But becauſe he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts <hi>God's Throne,</hi> ſitting in the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> impoſing his own Faith, Opinions, Creeds and Canons, (tail'd with a Fire-brand, an Anathema, a Curſe) againſt <hi>all</hi> Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, when <hi>he himſelf alſo is the greateſt</hi> Nonconformiſt;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62182:17"/>but keep moſt unjuſtly and unſufferably, both <hi>falſe Weights,</hi> and <hi>falſe Meaſures,</hi> one <hi>to buy</hi> by, and another <hi>to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> by as ſhall be ſhewn unanſwerably by and by.</p>
               <p>May we not therefore without any the <hi>leaſt Suſpition of Sawcineſs</hi> put this ſober Queſtion again, <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another Man's Servant?</hi> What is thy Name? Is it <hi>Lucifer?</hi> Is it <hi>Antichriſt</hi> or <hi>Man of Sin?</hi> Is <hi>that</hi> thy Name? <hi>Thou</hi> that like <hi>another</hi> God, <hi>ſitteſt there Domineering</hi> over Men's Faith, <hi>Lording</hi> it over God's Heritage; <hi>God's Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> who is the <hi>only Kardiagnoſtos,</hi> or Searcher of Hearts &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, where thou canſt take <hi>no</hi> Cognizance, if thou wouldſt judge?</p>
               <p>Who art thou, I ſay? <hi>Art thou a God,</hi> commanding the Waves, and ſaying, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou go, and no further, and here ſhall thy Proud Waves be ſtay'd?</hi> Art thou the <hi>Hercules-Pillars,</hi> or <hi>Hercules</hi> with his <hi>Club?</hi> Art thou the <hi>Ne Plus ultra</hi> in Religion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In Nomine Domini,</hi> What art thou? And where is <hi>thy Commiſſion,</hi> thy Authority? And who gave thee this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>to do theſe Things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our bleſſed Saviour commands us to call <hi>no Man</hi> Father, no Man <hi>Master</hi> upon Earth; that is, not implicitely <hi>jurare in Verba Magistri,</hi> to believe juſt as our Maſters, (our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) believe, becauſe Faith is not <hi>the Gift of a Synod,</hi> of a Convocation, of a Council, but is the <hi>Gift of God:</hi> And never was there Peace in the Chriſtian Church, ſince <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,</hi> and <hi>Synods,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> took upon them to make <hi>Acts of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> Impoſitions of Faith and Creeds, Curſing and Impriſoning, and ſometimes Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Starving all Gain ſayers; but by <hi>what</hi> Commiſſion?</p>
               <p>Is not this as irrational as that <hi>Cannon,</hi> and Decree of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſts, commanding all men on Pain of Fine and Impriſonment, to <hi>Believe</hi> that their two Gods (<hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>) never had <hi>been Men,</hi> when all the Countrey knew to the contrary? And ſome of them well remembred them
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62182:18"/>and had <hi>Eat</hi> and <hi>Drank</hi> with them? Moſt Excellent Bigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm!</p>
               <p>The firſt general Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had ſhamefully err'd but for <hi>Paphnutius,</hi> a poor Diſſenter, a One-ey'd Man that ſaw more than they all, and fet them to rights; and brought all the Biſhops to a better Sight and Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>The <hi>greateſt General Council</hi> that ever was in the Chriſtian World, was call'd and convocated at <hi>Ariminum;</hi> ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and odd Biſhops, <hi>twice as many Laun-ſleeves</hi> as was at <hi>Constantine's first great Council:</hi> And they all <hi>unanimouſly</hi> concluded <hi>against the Divinity</hi> of the ſecond Perſon of the Holy Trinity! <hi>Goodly Sleeves</hi> for a Man <hi>to pin his Faith upon!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanaſins</hi> that was <hi>ſuch a Stickler</hi> with his <hi>Creed,</hi> (that now <hi>bears his Name</hi> in the Common-Prayer-Book) <hi>Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Ending</hi> with an Anathema, to all that do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>juſt as he does;</hi> what <hi>got he</hi> by this Dogmatical <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his Faith</hi> upon all other Chriſtians? <hi>A Nick-name,</hi> the Age he liv'd in (very ungratefully ſome ſay) called him <hi>Sathanaſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it not enough for us</hi> to believe as our bleſſed Saviour ſays, that his <hi>Father is greater than he,</hi> and yet that <hi>he is one</hi> with <hi>his Father,</hi> God in Chriſt, and Chriſt in God, and Chriſt in Believers, that they alſo <hi>may be one</hi> with both?</p>
               <p>But where do we read in Scripture, that Chriſt is <hi>God of God, very God of very God?</hi> What language is this? The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreate,</hi> the Son <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreate,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreate,</hi> and yet they are not <hi>Three <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreate,</hi> but <hi>One <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreate:</hi> We are not <hi>Arrians,</hi> but ſurely the Holy Ghoſt in <hi>Scripture,</hi> has found <hi>ſufficient Words,</hi> and the Holy Scripture and Apoſtles Creed, is a <hi>ſufficient Rule of Faith;</hi> and ſurely was <hi>ſufficient</hi> to carry a man to <hi>Heaven</hi> three hundred years before <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> was born, and three hundred years before the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinopolitan-Creed</hi> was invented; and 1400 years before that <hi>Packt Convention at</hi> Trent, patch'd up with <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62182:18"/>Lord Biſhops, that were Shepherds without a Flock, yet had as good a <hi>Vote</hi> as the beſt: Is it not ſad that men <hi>muſt ſtarve and die,</hi> becauſe they obey not ſuch <hi>frothy Men</hi> (like Froth and Scum) <hi>becauſe uppermoſt?</hi> Is it not a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and ſhall <hi>be for a Lamentation,</hi> that <hi>all</hi> Chriſtian Men muſt be <hi>forc'd to ſee with other men's Eyes,</hi> and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve by <hi>Proxy,</hi> and obey <hi>Blindfold,</hi> and alſo ſwallow (like <hi>Cramm'd Capons</hi>) all that is put <hi>down their Throats?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not this <hi>Mahomet</hi>-like, who carried his Bible (his <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran</hi>) in <hi>one</hi> Hand, and his <hi>Sword</hi> in the <hi>other,</hi> ſaying, if the <hi>firſt</hi> will not do, the <hi>other ſhall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are all as <hi>good Church-of-England-Men</hi> as the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Men,</hi> we hope; Is it not enough for us (Church-of-<hi>England</hi> Men) to be <hi>Humble Seekers,</hi> and confeſs, with the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> that we <hi>mar err;</hi> and conſequently, it is unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to impoſe our Errors on others, and then <hi>back our Errors with Penal Laws;</hi> or to impoſe Creeds in <hi>other</hi> Words than the Holy Ghoſts Words, <hi>Scripture Words,</hi> which if <hi>Ambiguous,</hi> let us leave men to their <hi>own Maſter to ſtand or fall;</hi> to their own Judgments to <hi>Conſent</hi> or <hi>Diſſent,</hi> and never make theſe Impoſitions of Creeds an occaſion of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, or a <hi>Stumbling-Block</hi> in our <hi>Brothers way, to make him fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will men ſtill urge an <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which they themſelves <hi>keep not;</hi> made by a King, that this preſent King has publiſhed (whatſoever he was in his Life) a <hi>Papist at his Death,</hi> and made by a Parliament, diſtinguiſhed by (a Name <hi>Eternally Infamous</hi>) the <hi>Penſioners Parliament,</hi> from the multitude of <hi>Judas</hi>'s that ſold their, and their King and Countreys Conſciences, betray'd their Maſter by cheating His Exchequer, going <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ips with him</hi> in his Revenue, and like <hi>Ambo-Dexter-Lawyers,</hi> took <hi>Fees</hi> on both ſides, took Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Countrey to be faithful to their Intereſt, and then rook'd or robb'd the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> to <hi>betray the Countrey</hi> that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted them? O abominable <hi>Perfidy!</hi> Never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62182:19"/>nor forgiven, till a <hi>Brand</hi> be ſet upon them to <hi>mark them out</hi> to all Poſterity, for an Example of Treachery; and till they truly repent, which cannot be without <hi>Reſtitution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall a fellow be hang'd for taking a <hi>Purſe</hi> of <hi>Five Pounds</hi> value by the High-way? And ſhall they <hi>go <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npuniſh'd,</hi> that do not only betray <hi>their Trust;</hi> but rob the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Countrey too?</hi> Learned Lawyers have found Treaſon in it?</p>
               <p>If they had not been Purified by the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> and well <hi>Poiz'd</hi> by the honeſt Patriots in the Houſe of Commons, what miſchief might they not have done?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sometimes</hi> we read of the Church of <hi>Philippi, Epheſus, Galatia, Theſſalonia,</hi> &amp;c. There a <hi>National,</hi> there a <hi>City-Church,</hi> and ſometimes we read of the <hi>Church in thy Houſe;</hi> all <hi>true Churches,</hi> both the <hi>greater</hi> and the <hi>leſſer.</hi> So that the <hi>Church of England,</hi> are <hi>all the Faithful</hi> Chriſtians in <hi>England,</hi> and ought not to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Church'd, though they differ</hi> in ſmaller Ceremonies or greater Matters; for in the Church of <hi>Corinth, ſome denied</hi> the greateſt <hi>Fundamental in Divinity,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>without which</hi> all Preaching, Praying, Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are Null, Vold, and of no Effect, <hi>viz. The Reſurrection of the Dead;</hi> and yet they were <hi>in the Church,</hi> and no Apoſtolical Decree to Excommunicate them, or <hi>Caſt them out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How Unjuſtifiable then is it to <hi>Excommunicate</hi> a Believer, becauſe he Refuſes to Take the <hi>Church-Wardens Oath</hi> or <hi>Sacrament;</hi> or, for <hi>not Conforming</hi> to ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Trivial Concern?</p>
               <p>Are not <hi>they</hi> that <hi>thus</hi> Excommunicate, the <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> by laying a <hi>Scandal</hi> in their Brothers way, to <hi>make him fall, Rom.</hi> 15.13. and then by an Unchriſtian <hi>Capias;</hi> to Impriſon him, till Iris <hi>Purſe help</hi> him out?</p>
               <p>And a <hi>Proteſtants Abſolution</hi> (after all) coſts <hi>Ten times</hi> more Money, then is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Popiſh-Prieſts, in their Authentick and <hi>Printed Table of Fees, for Adultery</hi> or Inceſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that <hi>what Eaſe is it</hi> to a Proteſtant that lies ſtarving in a Goal (after he has ſtood Excommunicated 40 days) that <hi>it is not the Common Enemy</hi> has <hi>undone</hi> him, but a <hi>Proteſtant</hi>-Friend? Not the Briſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but one at <hi>home:</hi> If my Purſe, my Liberty, or my Goods be taken from me, 'tis a <hi>Cold Comfort</hi> to eaſe my Heart with this Melancholy Contemplation, that my <hi>Country-man,</hi> a <hi>Protestant</hi> did it, and <hi>not an Italian</hi> Prieſt; or, to eſcape the <hi>Romiſh-Fire</hi> and Faggot, or Bloody M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cres, (that ſoon puts us out of Pain) and yet be Crucified alive in a J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yle, <hi>a Man and his Houſe?</hi> Never do we read in Holy Scripture of a <hi>Convocation of Clergy-men,</hi> that took upon themſelves an Authority to <hi>make Canons,</hi> and lay <hi>Impoſitions upon the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ity, (no,</hi> not when even all <hi>the Chief Apoſtles</hi> were met in <hi>Synod,</hi> (at that <hi>only Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi> that holy Scripture ſpeaks of) at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) without the <hi>conſent</hi> of the <hi>Lay-Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Acts</hi> 15.23.</p>
               <p>And even <hi>(there)</hi> were not an <hi>innumerable</hi> company of Impoſitions and <hi>Canons.;</hi> Not ſo <hi>much as one</hi> Impoſition of Creeds to be believed: Nor <hi>any one</hi> Anathema, or Curſe, or Penal Law denounced againſt Diſſenters. Yet they had the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>Infallable</hi> Spirit of Truth, (which the Church of <hi>England</hi> does <hi>not in the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62182:19"/>to</hi>) and even then alſo enjoyned only a <hi>few neceſſary things. Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 15.28.</p>
               <p>And if <hi>either</hi> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or Church of <hi>England</hi> had not a Bigoted and <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridden Arm of Fleſh,</hi> wherewith to <hi>Fight Non-conformity;</hi> and would be <hi>content with ſuch Weapons as Chriſt</hi> and his holy Apoſtles thought ſufficient; they might Anatha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize, and Curſe, <hi>till their Hearts ſhould ake,</hi> before any Wiſe and Rational Chriſtian would believe as they believe, only becauſe they believed it: Who gave them <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> over our Faith and Conſciences? What <hi>Authority</hi> have they to <hi>Lord</hi> it over Gods Heritage, (the Layity? There, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. called Gods Clergy) eſpecially ſince, as ſhall be ſhown hereafter, they have Erred already, <hi>both in Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> That late Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> they <hi>now</hi> Smile at, and ſome of them, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>all Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> have <hi>Actually Recanted,</hi> Repented of, and Forſaken; or elſe we had ſin'd againſt the great <hi>Law</hi> of Nature, <hi>Self-Preſervation!</hi> Muſt we <hi>Pray againſt</hi> Arbitrary Government and Oppreſſion, and not uſe the means? May <hi>we not pay</hi> men in <hi>their own</hi> Coyn, and <hi>give</hi> them <hi>as good</hi> as they <hi>bring?</hi> May we not repell <hi>vim vi?</hi> Force <hi>with Force?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> is poyut-blanck againſt the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which <hi>Curſes all that dares deny,</hi> That it <hi>is Lawful to ſerve in the Wars?</hi> And if any War be Lawful, a <hi>Defenſive War</hi> (in defending <hi>Ours, or our Neighbours</hi> Lives, Houſes Goods, or Rights, as Men and Chriſtians) is (by <hi>all agreed</hi> to be) the <hi>moſt Lawful</hi> War, becauſe it is of abſolute <hi>neceſſity.</hi> For <hi>what</hi> has God and Nature furniſhed Men with <hi>Eyes,</hi> and Couragious <hi>Hearts,</hi> and ſtrong <hi>Arms?</hi> To keep our <hi>Arms in our Pockets</hi> till our Throats be Cut? We beg your Pardon. Mr. <hi>Paſſiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Obedience!</hi> Or if you will not <hi>give</hi> us Pardon, <hi>ſell</hi> it to us, as you do <hi>other</hi> Abſolutions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Of the Neceſſity of</hi> Changing and Recanting <hi>our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in</hi> Religion.</head>
               <p>IF any man (<hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Mahomet</hi>) ſay he has no <hi>Sin,</hi> he is a <hi>Liar,</hi> and the <hi>Truth is not in him;</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John</hi>) Then how is it poſſible for a Man to go to Heaven, except he <hi>Recant and R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pent;</hi> for Heaven is fill'd with <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0 glorified Saints,</hi> except <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>canters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No Book</hi> in the World is <hi>Faultleſs and Infallible</hi> (except the <hi>Holy Bible</hi>) for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Matter</hi> or <hi>Manner</hi> of Expreſſion, or <hi>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Taming</hi> the thing, or ſome <hi>other Circumſtance;</hi> it has ſome Errors or Faults in it.</p>
               <p>And <hi>if this be true,</hi> then <hi>every Author</hi> that writes a Book, <hi>ought to Recant</hi> the ſame, if he be a true Chriſtian; I mean, the <hi>Errors</hi> committed therein; for I never heard of any Chriſtian Man (as yet) that ever was <hi>ſo like the Father of Lies,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſire that any Body would <hi>Recant the Truth</hi>'s contained in his Ways, Books, or Works; The Truth <hi>will ſhift for its ſelf</hi> (in ſpight of all Oppoſition) <hi>at long run;</hi> but the <hi>Errours</hi> (of which <hi>no Man nor Book is free</hi>) ought to be <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nted,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly too, (if required) yea, as publickly as the <hi>Books</hi> that have been <hi>Publick.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62182:20"/>
               <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> has a large <hi>Recantation,</hi> and a <hi>Heavenly</hi> one, in Print, called, <hi>His Books of Confeſſions;</hi> ſo the Learned and Excellent <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and a Man (worth them all) St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Confeſſing and Recanting his <hi>Perſecuting</hi> Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is not in any Mortal Man's Power,</hi> to be free from Sin or <hi>Error; Homo ſum &amp; Humanum a me nibil alienum puto, at Humanum eſt Errare;</hi> was an old and too true a Proverb; If we be Mortals, we are ſubject to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and then <hi>if we be Chriſtians,</hi> or hope for Mercy, we muſt <hi>Recant:</hi> For though we may <hi>Err,</hi> (the Frail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aderſtandings</hi>) yet we need not be guilty of Hereſie or <hi>Obſtinacy</hi> in B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, (the fault of our <hi>Wills.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Thus the Church of <hi>England</hi> makes us all <hi>Recant publickly</hi> in the Church twice <hi>a Day,</hi> in ſober ſadneſs, if we do not Diſſemble, ſaying. <hi>We have left undone theſe things which we ought to have done; and we have done thoſe things which we ought not to have done; and there is no Health in us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt Learned and Elaborate <hi>Authors in our Age</hi> need no other Confutation of their humane <hi>Frailties and Errors,</hi> than their own <hi>Contradicting-Books;</hi> his pretty to ſhow, <hi>(if it more worth the while)</hi> how the <hi>Dean</hi> gives the <hi>Parſon</hi> the Lie; and the Arch-Deacon, the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and how deſperately <hi>they ſtabb themſelves,</hi> and are <hi>Felones de ſe,</hi> (in ſome ſence;) if a <hi>Lie deſerves a ſtab,</hi> they need, to other Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than their <hi>own,</hi> which is enough to abate <hi>the Huſſing Pride</hi> of the greateſt S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and <hi>Nobleſt Souls</hi> amongſt us, as well as to <hi>Mortifie the Bigot,</hi> that is ſo full, and <hi>puffe up with his preſent Notion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, Parliaments, Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Houſe of Commons, have <hi>Recanted,</hi> publickly bewailing, begging Pardon, and asking forgiveneſs of the <hi>Popes Nuntio</hi> (Cardinal <hi>Pool</hi>) on bended Knees; (when frighted with the Apprehenſions of Queen <hi>Maries Smithfield-F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res</hi>) and which is worſt of all, did for fear alſo <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant God</hi>'s Truth; at leaſt, they Recanted what the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Houſe of Commons had about ſix years before, by Statute-Law, <hi>Declared to be Gods Truth;</hi> 2 &amp; 3 Edw. 6. c. 1. and made by the <hi>Aid of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> (ſurely you'll ſay then, that muſt be the <hi>Bible</hi> which they recanted! And ſo one <hi>would think</hi> indeed; but it was a <hi>far Inferiour</hi> Buſineſs, <hi>viz.</hi> only) the <hi>Common Prayer-Book,</hi> ſaying, 1, and 2. <hi>Phil</hi> and <hi>Mar. c.</hi> 8. <hi>Seeing by the goodneſs of God our own Errors, have knowledged the ſame to the ſaid moſt Reverend Father,</hi> (Cardinal <hi>Pool,</hi> the Popes Legate) Therefore, <hi>We the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons Aſſembled in this preſent Parliament, Repreſenting the whole Body of the Realm of</hi> ENGLAND, <hi>&amp;c. Do Declare our ſelves very ſorry, and Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntant</hi> (Poor Hearts!) <hi>of the Schiſm and Diſobedience,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>againſt the See Apoſtolick,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And all this <hi>Recantation,</hi> the Biſhops and Parliament, (when the times turn'd) <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant again</hi> about five years after, in 1 <hi>Elig.</hi> 1. Reſuming again this ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Peayer-Book, and ſetting up a <hi>High-Commiſſion-Court,</hi> &amp;c. which was for Cruelties and Oppreſſions, Condemn'd by (17 Car. 1.2.)</p>
               <p>And when the King and Parliament were offended, becauſe Biſhops were <hi>too buſie,</hi> or too much buſied in <hi>Temporal Employments,</hi> Powers and Authorities; they were <hi>Diſabled</hi> by (17 Car. 1.27.) but made <hi>Capable</hi> again, by (13 Car. 2.2.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Variation of the Compaſs</hi> is here? What Turnings and <hi>Windings,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnings</hi> again? Then <hi>Facing about</hi> as you were; (of which I might give many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Inſtances) let this ſuffice for <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62182:20"/>
               <p>And if we croſs the Seas, and make a <hi>Progreſs</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> to the <hi>Infallible</hi> Chair, we ſhall find that even that too, ſtands as unſteady, or <hi>more unſteady</hi> than any other; In proof whereof, I'll have <hi>no other Vouchers</hi> than Papiſts and <hi>Cardinals;</hi> and for Cleanlineſs ſake give but a ſmall Touch at the dirty Work.</p>
               <p>Was not the Bones of Pope <hi>Formoſus</hi> digged up by the <hi>Pope</hi> his Succeſſor, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees <hi>Reſcinded,</hi> and the poor Dead <hi>Pope</hi> thrown into <hi>Tyber</hi> for a <hi>Heretick,</hi> not worthy of <hi>Chriſtian Burial,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>Platina, Theodore.</hi> 197. and <hi>John</hi> 10.897. tells us. That Pope <hi>Theodore</hi> II. made Null and Void the Decrees of <hi>Romanus.</hi> And did not Pope <hi>John</hi> X. do as much for him? I care not <hi>which was in the Right;</hi> it ſufficeth my preſent purpoſe to ſhew, That <hi>one of the Infallible Don's</hi> did Err, and was Fallible.</p>
               <p>And does not Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> (<hi>ad an.</hi> 900) on this Score, cry out, Alas! <hi>For Shame and Sorrow, that ſo many Monſters (a horrible thing to ſee) ſhould mount that Chair, which deſerves</hi> (Sir) <hi>Reverence of Angels?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Was not <hi>Pope Bennet</hi> IX. made Pope at twelve years of Age, by the means of his Father the Marqueſs of <hi>Tuſeta,</hi> and could not ſo much as read Maſs? And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>skill'd in nothing</hi> but the <hi>Black Art,</hi> by which the <hi>Letcher</hi> (as Cardinal <hi>Benno</hi> affirms,) enticed pretty <hi>Wenches</hi> into the Woods, and there Debanch'd them: Well might Cardinal <hi>Barronius (ad An.</hi> 1033.) call him, The Shame of the Romiſh Church, <hi>Eccleſiae Opprobrium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Does not <hi>Luithrand</hi> (lib. 2. c. 3.) tell us, That the Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> did De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Pope <hi>John</hi> XII? Firſt, for Ordaining Deacons in a <hi>Stable:</hi> Secondly, For making Boys (but ten years of Age) <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Thirdly, For <hi>Praying to the Devil to help him</hi> (when he was at Dice) <hi>to a lucky Throw.</hi> Fourthly, For making his Houſe (the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teran</hi>-Palace) a <hi>Common Stews.</hi> Fifthly, For lying with <hi>Stephana,</hi> his own Fathers Whore. Sixthly, For Drinking a Health to the Devil.</p>
               <p>Does not <hi>Platina</hi> (<hi>Silveſt.</hi> 2. <hi>An.</hi> 998.) tell us. That Pope <hi>Sylvester</hi> II. made a Bargain with the Devil, to give him Body and Soul, upon two Conditions; Firſt, That the Devil would help him into the Infallible Chair: Secondly, That he ſhould never die but in <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> whither he was reſolved never to come. The Contract thus made, the Devil helpt him to the Popedom; <hi>Pontificatum, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurante Diabolo conſecutus eſt, hâc tamen lege, ut poſt Mortem totus illius eſſet.</hi> But the Devil was as crafty as a <hi>Jeſuice,</hi> for he cheated, with an Equivocation, the <hi>Pope himſelf,</hi> who Died horribly, (<hi>C. Malmesbur.</hi> 2.10.) whilſt he was <hi>ſaying Maſs in Rome,</hi> in the Church, called <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might fill Volumns with theſe Inſtances, to ſhew that even Popes ought to change and <hi>Recant,</hi> if ever they hope to be <hi>Saved;</hi> for there are no <hi>good Men</hi> here on Earth, nor <hi>Glorified Saints</hi> in Heaven. except Recanters! Honeſt <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> have Recanted, St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine, Beza,</hi> and all <hi>Honeſt Men,</hi> have Recanted: And muſt not all good Proteſtants then come into the Faſhion of all good Men in Heaven and Earth?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62182:21"/>
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>Of the Reſtraint of the</hi> PRINTING-PRESS.</head>
               <p>PRinting, though reckon'd amongſt <hi>the New Inventions,</hi> is <hi>now</hi> become <hi>an Old Trade</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and has <hi>begot one or two</hi> more Trades; the <hi>Book-ſellor</hi> and <hi>Stationer,</hi> which are all Incorporated into a <hi>Body-Politick;</hi> called, <hi>The Company of Stationers;</hi> no deſpicable <hi>nor mean</hi> Company (or Hall) in this ſplendid City; one <hi>Stationer was enough</hi> for a City, before <hi>Printing</hi> came up; and of <hi>Book-ſellers</hi> there were none, but <hi>Scriveners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>now</hi> they are become the <hi>Numerous Iſſue</hi> of the Preſs; and enabled to make <hi>By-Laws</hi> for the Regulating their Trade; which is <hi>their Lively-hood:</hi> And the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, Whether it be reaſonable and lawful to <hi>hinder them of their Lively-hood,</hi> of their <hi>Trade,</hi> under pretence of Publique-good, by <hi>ſhutting up the Preſs,</hi> and ſtopping their Trade, by <hi>excluding all</hi> that have not a Paſſe, (and ſome ſay you may <hi>with as much reaſon</hi> Exclude all men from the <hi>Kings-High-Way,</hi> the Birth-light of every <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſk-man,</hi> or ſtop their Mouths and ſtarve them) except they <hi>bring a Paſſe</hi> Sign'd by Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> the Biſhops Chaplain, <hi>or the like;</hi> to permit them to <hi>Earn</hi> their Livings?</p>
               <p>There's an Act of Parliament for it you'll ſay; and for that Trick. I ſay, I'll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine nothing <hi>poſitively</hi> againſt it.</p>
               <p>But, Acts of Parliament <hi>are not like the Laws</hi> of the <hi>Medes and Perſians,</hi> which cannot be <hi>alter'd.</hi> The <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Prieſts told <hi>Herodotus</hi> that the Sun had <hi>chang'd it's courſe</hi> four times within the laſt Preceding <hi>Eleven thouſand and</hi> odd years; an <hi>Aera,</hi> as long before <hi>Adam,</hi> as ſince.</p>
               <p>But, if the <hi>Sun</hi> change it's courſe <hi>ſometimes,</hi> and the <hi>Moon often times,</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> change their Acts <hi>ſometimes twice in Ten Years,</hi> as afore-ſaid; then ſurely <hi>this Act for Reſtraint of the Preſs</hi> (without the Licenſe of the Biſhops Chaplain or Sir <hi>Roger, &amp;c.</hi>) is not <hi>immutable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Arguments to keep the <hi>Preſs-doors ſhut,</hi> center all in this. That a Liberty thereof, <hi>without the Paſs of a Licenſe,</hi> may prove pernicious <hi>not only</hi> to private men, but to <hi>the Publique,</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> to the <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Libels will <hi>fly about to wound</hi> mens Reputations; and, which is a conſideration of greater weight. The Church and State may thus be ſhot at and mounded, and yet like ſhooting with <hi>White Powder,</hi> the Wound is <hi>felt,</hi> but none knows <hi>whence</hi> the Bullets came.</p>
               <p>This is an Inconvenience; but, <hi>if this be all,</hi> the Argument is <hi>fallacious:</hi> For, as in <hi>other</hi> Trades, things that are <hi>rare,</hi> dear <hi>and hard to come by,</hi> are the <hi>readieſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity;</hi> ſo alſo in the <hi>Book-ſellers</hi> Trade, no Books vend <hi>ſo nimbly,</hi> as thoſe that are ſold (by <hi>Stealth</hi> as it were) and want <hi>Imprimaturs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Reſtraint by Licenſers</hi> will not prevent the <hi>flying Pamphlets</hi> and Reputation-Wounders; we may well ſay, <hi>it will not,</hi> becauſe by Experience 'tis found <hi>it never did.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62182:21"/>
               <p>But, if the <hi>By-Law already made</hi> by the <hi>Stationers Company,</hi> were Enacted by <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> with ſome <hi>additions,</hi> all the Inconveniencies of <hi>Reſtraining the Preſs from Printing the beſt Books,</hi> (becauſe it is perh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ps againſt the <hi>Diana of Mr. Licenſer,</hi> or the <hi>Craft by which he gets his Wealth</hi>) will be prevented; and all the <hi>Reputation-Wounders</hi> will be diſcovered, and without <hi>further Proof,</hi> brought to Cendign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: Namely, A Law, that every <hi>Author</hi>'s and <hi>Printer</hi>'s Name, and their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of <hi>Reſidence,</hi> and the mans Name for whom they were <hi>Printed,</hi> and who <hi>Publiſhes</hi> and <hi>Vends</hi> them, be Printed in the <hi>Title-Page</hi> of every Book or Pamphlet; And that ſuch <hi>Printed Names</hi> ſhall be a ſufficient Evidence, as if under their own <hi>Hand-Writting;</hi> provided it be proved by <hi>Witneſſes and Writing,</hi> that the Author gave <hi>order</hi> for it (and that the Printer (there named) did <hi>really Print</hi> the ſame:) And that it ſhall be <hi>Felony,</hi> (or ſome Crime or Puniſhment) to Print any Book or Pamphlet in other manner; or to Print <hi>falſe Names:</hi> Or with what other <hi>Proviſo's</hi> the Wiſdom of a Parliament ſhall think meet.</p>
               <p>The Pope indeed <hi>has ſome Reaſon</hi> to Reſtrain all Printing, without his <hi>Approbation Licenſe,</hi> or <hi>Instruction;</hi> becauſe it is very meet and right ſo to do; granting his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, An <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi> is a <hi>neceſſary</hi> and juſt <hi>Conſequence</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p>But, Church of <hi>England, that diſclaims all ſuch Impudent pretence;</hi> what Reaſon <hi>can ſhe give</hi> to be the <hi>only Door-keeper</hi> to the Preſs, except ſhe could alſo get an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> that it ſhall not be <hi>Lawful</hi> hereafter for <hi>God Almighty</hi> to open any mans Underſtanding clearer, nor to give him <hi>better Eyes</hi> then the <hi>Licenſer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, How many Excellent Books, both in <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Humanity,</hi> are Suppreſs'd, <hi>becauſe they are excellent, and too good</hi> to get an <hi>Imprimatur?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This made the Great Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> ſay, That the Clergy have but <hi>one Vote;</hi> for the Inſeriour Clergy generally think themſelves notably ſharp-ſighted in Affairs, if they can but <hi>look up to the Top</hi> of the Church-Steeple, and ſee how <hi>the Cock ſtands;</hi> and as the Wind blows, <hi>many</hi> of them ſometimes <hi>Conform</hi> themſelves.</p>
               <p>Thus Haggards liſten to the Huntſmans <hi>Halloo</hi> and <hi>Horn,</hi> but ſeldome put their <hi>Noſes to the Ground</hi> to examine the Scent; For which the Huntſman Whips them <hi>ſmartly</hi> ſometimes, yet 'tis <hi>all one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No men are greater Vaſſals then ſmall Clergy-men, or at leaſt <hi>more Oppreſs'd</hi> with unreaſonable <hi>Aſſents</hi> and <hi>Conſents,</hi> in ſpight of Mathematicks, and illegal Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Synodals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> even <hi>when there is no Synod,</hi> no Viſitation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet <hi>(poor Hearts)</hi> they out with their Purſe, and pay the Biſhops Silver, and the Rich Arch-Deacons Silver, though ſome of them <hi>Pawa the Pewter-Diſh for it;</hi> and yet for all this V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſallage, ſome of them does not ſo much as Whimper, Groan, nor Complain, nor Vote otherwiſe then (as the Word is <hi>Ecchoed</hi> amongſt them) though at ſuch a time as this, when a Parliament <hi>can</hi> help us.</p>
               <p>Thus have I ſeen a <hi>Step-Mother</hi> Whip the Child till it <hi>Roar</hi> again, and then take it up again and Whip it for <hi>Roaring;</hi> and then make it go down on its <hi>Knees,</hi> aſk <hi>Forgiveneſs, Kiſs the Rod;</hi> threatning to give it <hi>twice as much</hi> if it tell it's <hi>Father:</hi> But come on't what will, I will ſay—<hi>God help,</hi> the while.</p>
               <p>Has <hi>any man</hi> in the World <hi>any other or better</hi> Commiſſion to Preach, then what Chriſt gave his Diſciples? (Mat. 28.19.) namely, <hi>To go and teach,</hi> and make all <hi>Nations</hi> Diſciples by Baptizing them; and he will be <hi>with ſuch</hi> to the end of the World; not with thoſe Individual Apoſtles (who are <hi>dead</hi>) but their Succeſſours (Lawfully ordain'd) to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue end of the World.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62182:22"/>
               <p>Let any <hi>man ſhow me a Reaſon</hi> if he can, why a Presbyter <hi>Lawfully ordain'd,</hi> and therefore <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> by Chriſt to <hi>Teach all Nations, &amp;c.</hi> ſhould need <hi>any other</hi> Licenſe? And is not <hi>teaching</hi> in Print from the <hi>Preſs,</hi> the ſame or better, and of <hi>more general</hi> and univerſal <hi>benefit</hi> to all-men, and <hi>all Nations,</hi> then the <hi>narrow Pulpit,</hi> though it ſtand <hi>aloft?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And dare any Chriſtian prefer the Worth of an Act of Parliament, before the <hi>Words of God</hi> and our Lord Jeſus, who has commanded <hi>all Men to let their Light ſo ſhine before Men, that they may ſee their good Works,</hi> (in Print, the moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, Univerſal, and Charitable Good Works in the World, if they be agreeable to Holy Scripture, and right Reaſon) and glorifie their Father <hi>which is in Heaven,</hi> without leave or Licenſe?</p>
               <p>Does not our Law-Books ſay, That all Statutes are <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> Void, if againſt the <hi>Common Law,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the Light of Reaſon, or Law of Nature) or againſt the <hi>Law of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is againſt the <hi>Common Law</hi> to take away, or Obſtruct any Mans Trade or Birthright, <hi>(as Printing is to many Men)</hi> when the Publick, <hi>the State and the Church,</hi> and every <hi>private</hi> Man's Reputation, may be better and ſufficiently Enſured by other Ways?</p>
               <p>Is there not a Poſitive Law of Chriſt to all Chriſtians; not to hide their T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>a Napkin,</hi> (though the Licenſers for Self-Intereſt, will not give us an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> to improve it?)</p>
               <p>Is there not a Plain-Law of Chriſt, That we ſhould not put <hi>our Light under a Buſhel,</hi> but on a <hi>Candleſtick,</hi> that all that come in may ſee the Light? The Liberty of the Pulpit, Bench or Preſs, are the <hi>Golden Candleſticks;</hi> the Self-ended <hi>Imprima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi>'s very Wooden Ones, (God knows) if this little Treatiſe cannot be Gain-ſaid nor Confuted, but by the Goaler?</p>
               <p>Is there not a Poſitive Law of Chriſt; <hi>Not to quench the Spirit?</hi> And ſhall any <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Law</hi> quench it, for Self-ends, and becauſe they are ſo mad as to ſhut their Eyes, and ſcorn to amend, or be cured by a charitable Hand, that is willing to do it for God's ſake, and not for any other Fee?</p>
               <p>Since then there is a <hi>Poſitive Law</hi> of Chriſt to let our Light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee our <hi>Good and Charitable Works,</hi> (in Print to chuſe) that <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> (which is in Heaven) <hi>may be Glorified;</hi> Then let us give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars;</hi> but let us not rob God, to give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are Gods Peculiars and Property.</p>
               <p>And what <hi>Honeſt</hi> Proteſtant would not think it much more Honour to be <hi>God's Advocate,</hi> (in ſuch a Book as this, (as little as it is,) Pſeading <hi>Gods Cauſe,</hi> his Right and Bole Dominion over Conſciences, than by Invading Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (Gods Throne) to <hi>arrive to the higheſt Preſerments,</hi> (the Effect of Favour (many times) or ſome wilder Chance?)</p>
               <p>And now have I done with the Five Chapters which are all Uniform and of a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ece; there went but the Sacars (or Sections) between them, for Methods ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>AND now (Moſt Excellent Patriots!) I'll Conclude with the <hi>Honeſt Confeſſion</hi> of a <hi>Popiſh Prieſt,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> (in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntaries upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.13.) <hi>Ye are the Salt of the Earth, but if the
<pb facs="tcp:62182:22"/>Salt has loſt its Savour,</hi> &amp;c. And juſt as he was Writing upon that Text, the <hi>French</hi> Souldiers had broke into <hi>Rome,</hi> (<hi>May</hi> 6. 1527) and us'd the <hi>Clergy</hi> (above all others) <hi>moſt ſcurvily and abominably.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon, (ſaith he) <hi>Evanuimus, ac ad nibilum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tiles, niſi ad Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternas Ceremonias, Externague bona,</hi> &amp;c. We the Prelates of <hi>Rome,</hi> do now <hi>by woful Experience,</hi> find the <hi>Truth of this Scripture</hi> this day, being become, not only a <hi>Laughing-Stock,</hi> but a <hi>Prey</hi> (not to <hi>Inſidels,</hi> but) to <hi>Christians,</hi> by God's moſt righteous Judgment; becauſe we, who by <hi>our Functions</hi> ſhould have been the <hi>Salt of the Earth,</hi> had loſt our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> and were good for little but looking after <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and the <hi>Revenues of the Church:</hi> Hence it is, that <hi>together with us,</hi> this whole City <hi>comes to be troden under foot</hi> this day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in <hi>England</hi> (for ought we know to the contrary) is <hi>as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> as our <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> (as to the generality of it) may ſerve the <hi>Turn</hi> (it was made for) well enough; yet it appears to be made by no other <hi>Aid of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> than other Prayer-Books in Print, if ſo much.</p>
               <p>Both of theſe main Pillars of our Church are <hi>miſerably Dilapidated</hi> and out of frame, from top to bottom; yet not ſo ghaſtly, but they may by You, be well enough repaired, without pulling down.</p>
               <p>If this be accounted a <hi>Slander</hi> caſt upon Mother-Church, or that any <hi>be ſo blind,</hi> as not to ſee what is ſo <hi>plain</hi> and obvious to every conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Eye, that is not blinded with her Dowry; (like that <hi>young Gallant,</hi> who being demanded why he would <hi>Wed ſuch an Old Woman,</hi> though ſhe was very <hi>Rich,</hi> (ſtudying what he ſhould ſee in her to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage</hi> the fondneſs of his Embraces) anſwered, that he could not but <hi>love her very Wrinkles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Wrinckles, I had rather <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſque</hi> over and cover, than <hi>diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;</hi> I hate the ungrateful Work; except I be call'd upon to <hi>Prove my Words,</hi> and to ſhow her Nakedneſs and Diſtempers, through her whole Conſtitution: It is ſo far out of frame, that it is a wonder to me, that it has ſtood ſo well, and ſo long.</p>
               <p>But you may eaſily repair her Breaches, which I am ready to prove have diſtracted theſe Nations, theſe fifty years and more, and of ſuch abſolute Neceſſity to be mended, that no man hereafter (high or low) ſhall give his Aſſent and Conſent, (as all we Clergy-Men have done) under our Hands; except <hi>we Wink</hi> when <hi>we Write,</hi> and Subſcribe Blindfold, in ſpight of our Knowledge and Conſciences, and in ſpight of Mathematicks.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:62182:23"/>
               <p>And what a ſhame is it, that Clergy-Men from the Higheſt to the loweſt, ſhall be forc'd (as now) to ſtarve, or Subſcribe to an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, or Iniquity, becauſe Eſtabliſhed by a Law, (the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity?</hi>) that condſiering how, and when it was made, 'tis a Miracle to me, that they had not got <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pery</hi> as well Eſtabliſhed by a Law, but that the <hi>Major Part</hi> of that <hi>Penſioners Parliament</hi> were honeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>But if after all this, ſome <hi>Achitophel,</hi> ſome <hi>Machiavilian,</hi> who has got more <hi>Power</hi> than <hi>Grace,</hi> will confute me only, (as the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> confuted thoſe two Excellent Proteſtants (as aforeſaid) only with a <hi>Jayl:</hi> He will in the end prove himſelf to be a true <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel,</hi> (as the Name ſignifies in the <hi>Hebrew Tongue</hi>) <hi>Coſen-German to a Fool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And may glory a while (and but a while, I hope) as the <hi>French</hi> King does, that in making new Converts, and upholding his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; His <hi>Dragoons</hi> and his Jaylors are his <hi>beſt Breachers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſo; then, <hi>moſt Noble Healers of our Breaches!</hi> Let not <hi>Proteſtants</hi> hereafter be permitted to <hi>force</hi> your Subjects (who have <hi>entruſted</hi> you with Power) to the ſad Choice (which <hi>Papiſts</hi> glory in) namely, To <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> the Croſs, or <hi>Bear</hi> the Croſs; ſtretch your <hi>Conſciences,</hi> or ſtretch a <hi>Halter; Bow</hi> or we will <hi>Break</hi> your Necks, or <hi>Starve you</hi> in a Jayle</p>
               <p>But I humbly ſay — If <hi>here</hi> I have ſpoke Evil, <hi>bear Witneſs</hi> of the Evil; but, <hi>if well,</hi> why <hi>ſmiteſt</hi> thou me through Envy? Envy, that Rancour, Ruſt and Canker of Man's Soul (that like the Wood Worm) Eats up and <hi>Devours</hi> its Parent that breeds it and feeds it.</p>
               <p>Nay, for the <hi>ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting work too,</hi> I am very willing to <hi>ſubmit</hi> my Skull to <hi>be ſtoned to Death</hi> for any <hi>the least Errour</hi> in this Treatiſe committed, upon condition, that <hi>he</hi> only <hi>that is free from Errour</hi> caſt <hi>the firſt Stone</hi> at me.</p>
               <p>I do not <hi>much Tremble</hi> at this <hi>Frank and Free</hi> Offer, though I be <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted</hi> with (the Preſent Pope) <hi>Old Innocent Himſelf,</hi> or any <hi>of his</hi> Biſhops.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>COLCHESTER,</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>January.</hi> 17. 1688/7.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Errata. In the Epiſtle, Page 3. Line 28. for <hi>Males Administration,</hi> read <hi>Male-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration.</hi> Page 4. Line 28. for <hi>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> read <hi>ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
